<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine &amp; profitable catechisme whereunto is added a sermon preached upon Exod.23.2. / By that reverend and judicious divine Mr James Bacon, late minister of Burgate in Suffolke. Now first published by his son in law H.W.</title>
            <author>Bacon, James, minister of Burgate, Suffolk.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1853_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1853_3*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869155</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170467</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170467)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 231:E1853[3] or 231:E1853[3*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine &amp; profitable catechisme whereunto is added a sermon preached upon Exod.23.2. / By that reverend and judicious divine Mr James Bacon, late minister of Burgate in Suffolke. Now first published by his son in law H.W.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, James, minister of Burgate, Suffolk.</author>
                  <author>Perkins, William, 1558-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48, 59-145, [3], 1-69, 80-85, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Hall for R. Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. M DC LX. [1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The catechism is for students, not children, and is a theological treatise in connexion with William Perkins's works -- Madan.</note>
                  <note>"The sinfulness of compliance with a multitude in sinning" has a separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous = Thomason E.1853[3*].</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Exodus XXIII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170467:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLAINE &amp; PROFITABLE CATECHISME Whereunto is Added A SERMON Preached upon <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By that Reverend and Judicious Divine</hi> Mr JAMES BACON, <hi>late Miniſter of Burgate in Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now firſt Publiſhed by his Son in Law <hi>H.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2</hi> Tim. <hi>2.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hold faſt the forme of Sound words.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Hall</hi> for <hi>R. Davis Anno Dom.</hi> MDCLX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170467:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170467:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER</head>
            <p>THIS Solid, Pithy <hi>Catechiſme</hi> which holds forth <hi>the Forme of ſound words,</hi> and this excellent. <hi>Sermon</hi> tending much to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I received from the hands of a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and grave Matron, an <hi>old Diſciple,</hi> and ſtedfaſt Christian the ſurviver of her Deare Husband the worthy Author. After deliberate peruſall of what is here preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to publik view. I cannot but give this Teſtimony to the truth that heres an <hi>Iliad</hi> in a Nutſhell, I meane a great deale of good profitable matter compriſed in a Narrow roome: ther's much in a little and that which is ſound and Orthodox. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I never had any perſonall acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the reverend Author yet having contracted affinitie with his Family (to
<pb facs="tcp:170467:3"/>which I be are great reſpect) &amp; likewiſe for his choiſe worke and profitable Labors in the Miniſtry (An evident Teſtimony I have from ſeverall manuſcripts, which I have ſeeen) I conceive my ſelfe obliged to to make an honourable mention of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Divine, being one of thoſe whom the Apoſtle would have highly eſteemed of, <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.12, 13. And we beſeech you Brethren to know them, which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord and admoniſh you, and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake.</hi> As for the worke (becauſe there's ſo much worth as abundantly to commend it ſelfe) I need add no more.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Author who livd a ſaint on earth and (I queſtion not) is now a ſaint in glory, becauſe he is out of the reach of feare, and flateries, I ſhall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a particular or two, of ſpeciall obſervation worthy of Imitation. What I ſhall make mention of I'le reduce unto two heads. <hi>1.</hi> Before he entred into the Miniſtrie. <hi>2.</hi> After he was ſetled in a Paſtorall Cure.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Before he entred itto to the Miniſtry he was a hopefull ſtudious Scholler in <hi>Emanuel Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi> a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb facs="tcp:170467:3"/>eminent for Religion and Learning. And he had a
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr John Preſton.</note> Tutor there of great worth and abilitie the glory of the place where he lived. There he made great profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie in Religion and Learning wherefore being well qualifyd to fix upon a calling, his
<note n="*" place="margin">Sir James Bacon.</note> Father a Knight of great Qualitie ſent to him, that he would have him be a Lawyer, and to that purpoſe he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverfity to one of the Inns of Court: whereupon he anſwered (as I can produce his letter for proofe hereof) with much reverence to his Father, uſed ſtrong reaſons for his great deſire to give himſelfe to the worke of the Miniſtry: And notwithſtanding his Fathers frequent ſollicitations, yet he (ſhewing all duty and obſervance to him) perſiſted in the reſolution which God fixt in his heart, and retained it inviolably which was to dedicate himſelfe to Chriſt in the worke of the Goſpell; Whereunto his Father yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as being prevailed withall, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the ſtrength of his Sons Reaſons, ſo that it hence evidently appeares, that he took upon him the Miniſteriall Function not upon neceſſity but choyce, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainedly, but willingly, not for ſiniſter reſpects &amp; ſelf-intereſts but for Gods glory.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:170467:4"/> 
               <hi>3.</hi> After he entred into the Miniſtrie having been Lecturer ſeverall yeares at <hi>Bow in Cheapſide at London</hi> where his name is freſh and green (as I have heard) amongſt ſome ancient Profeſſors yet alive: he removed to <hi>Burgate in Suffolke,</hi> where he exerciſed his miniſtry for many yeares, and there finiſhed his courſe. He was in all his Relations as Paſtor, Husband, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Maſter, Faithfull, Loving, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious, one who walked by the rule of David in <hi>Pſal. 101.</hi> His godly converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, learning, wiſdome, charity are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly known to many, not only in his own Pariſh, but likewiſe in the adjacent pariſhes where he lived. And let this be mentioned as a Character of honour for the Perpetuating of his memorie, and for a patterne of imitation, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſore and grievous bodily infirmities by the ſtone, ſtrangury &amp;c. yet (when he could not goe of himſelfe) he would be carryed to the Publick Congregation, and there Prach the Goſpell. I ſhall not make a larger Preface to ſo ſhort a Volumne; yett his Motto may be fitly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the enſuing worke. <hi>Pondere non numero.</hi> Throughout the whole there's ſound Doctrine plainely and profitably
<pb facs="tcp:170467:4"/>handled. If therehy thou profiteſt <hi>(Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> and ſo thou mayſt if it be not thy owne fault give God the glory and labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be more grounded and ſtabliſhed in the truths that are in Jeſus, And ſo I remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy ſouls Servant <hi>H. W.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>OXON. <date>May <hi>2. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:170467:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170467:5"/>
            <head>A PRACTICALL CATECHISME, Introductory to a large expoſition of Reverend Mr <hi>PERKINS</hi> his CATECHISME.</head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHy art thou called a Chriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe I profeſſe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Chriſtian Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſtian Religion is a Heavenly Art, or a wholſome Doctrine according to Godlineſſe, revealed and taught by Chriſt, ſhewing us the right way to eternall life. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1, 2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> v. 9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.68.17.3.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is Chriſtian Religion called a Doctrine according to Godlineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is a patterne of Gods moſt holy will: and that excellent Rule which Chriſt hath given us to walk by, <hi>teaching us to deny ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent world.</hi> Tit. 2.11, 12.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170467:6"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>Are all thoſe Chriſtians that are ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: to make a Chriſtian indeed theſe three things muſt concurre. 1. Sound knowledge: 2. Faith unfained: 3. Holy obedience. They and they only are Chriſtians indeed, the only true Chriſtians ſuch as are truly ingrafted into Chriſt. who have attained to the true knowledge of God and have put on Chriſt by Faith; and yeild obedience to the Doctrine of Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26, 27. <hi>Rom.</hi> ch. 6. v. 17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Tell me then, what is required of thoſe that have taken upon them the honourable title of Chriſtians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt they muſt be diligent in learning the Heavenly art of Chriſtianity <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.32, 34. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly they muſt earneſtly contend for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, <hi>Jude v.</hi> 3. Thirdly they muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by a holy and unblameable life to adorne the Doctrine of Chriſt. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where is the Christian Religion taught?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the writings of the Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which are called the holy Scriptures. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What were theſe Prophets and Apoſtles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were Teachers called, and ſent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by God; inſtructed by Chriſt himſelfe; and infallibly aſſiſted by the holy Ghoſt in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Doctrines delivered to the Church, either by word, or writing. And therefore the Doctrine of of the Prophets, and Apoſtles is to be received, and embraced as the Doctrine of Chriſt. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.70.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170467:6"/>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Joh:</hi> 16.13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why are the writings of the Prophets and Apostles called the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Scripture is a Latine word, which ſignifieth writing: now becauſe, of all writings that ever were publiſhed, theſe are the worthieſt, therefore (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by an excellency) they are ſtiled the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Why are they called the Holy Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Scriptures are holy in theſe 4. reſpects,</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe the holy Ghoſt did indite, and dictate whatſoever is written in this precious Book. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe the Penmen of Scripture were holy men of God, holy Prophets and holy Apoſtles. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.70. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>Thirdly becauſe the holy will of God is here revealed: whatſoever is recorded in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is an holy Truth; <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.5. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.72. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.6.</p>
            <p>Fourthly becauſe the word is a powerfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, whereby the elect of God are ſanctified and made holy. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Seeing the Scriptures are ſo holy, whether may Lay people read them and ſpeake of them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes they may read them, ſo they addreſſe themſelves to the reading of them with holy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: they may ſpeake of them ſo they ſpeake of them with reverence, and alleadge them to thoſe holy ends for which they were written; as to gaine ſome glory to God, who is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170467:7"/>of holy writ: and to edifie one another in their Chriſtian Faith. <hi>Jude. v.</hi> 20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But many think, that it belongs to Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men only to ſearch and Study the Scripture: tell me therefore whether is it a duty that God requires of all Chriſtians to read and ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, all the diſciples of Chriſt (that are able to reade) ought to reade and ſearch the Scriptures as well Lay-men, as Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may that appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By theſe arguments,</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe the precepts enjoyning this duty are generall, and extend as well to the Lay-People, as to Miniſters. Reade <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Secondly we have examples of all ſorts recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture, which ſhew, that this exerciſe of pietie is commendable in all ages, in all degrees and callings, Read 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God hath made ſuch gracious Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as may encourage all Chriſtians to performe this dutie. Reade <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that which was written to all, &amp; is commended to be read unto all. why ſhould it not be free for all to reade. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 7. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. But the Scriptures are obſcure and hard to be underſtood, and therefore ſimple and unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men cannot profit by reading of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170467:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Scriptures are in themſelves perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, and plaine enough: They are written in ſuch a ſtyle as is moſt fit for the Inſtruction of the whole Church, yea all things that are neceſſarie to be known and believed of all men to ſalvation are plainly and manifeſtly layd down in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And therfore all ſorts of men may profit by reading of them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.130. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.115. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Seeing you affirme the Scriptures to be in themſelves perſpicuous, and yet they ſeeem darke to many that read them, tell me therefore to whom are the Scriptures plaine and eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To Spirituall and Regenerate Perſons, uſing the meanes, which God hath appointed to bring us to the right underſtanding of the Scriptures. <hi>All the words of wiſdome are plaine to him that underſtandeth. Prov.</hi> 8.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>But to naturall, and carnall men, neglecting the meanes they ſeem very darke, and obſcure. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Tell me then what are the ordinarie Meanes, which are to be uſed to bring us to the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Humble and fervent prayers unto God: we muſt entreat the Lord to open the eyes of our underſtanding, that ſo we may underſtand the Scriptures. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.18, 68. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.45. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.2.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170467:8"/> 2. Frequent and attentive reading, with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideration of all the circumſtances of the Text.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conference of other places: we muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Scripture with Scripture, and expound one place of Scripture by another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We muſt get humble and docible hearts: we muſt read the word with a deſire to learne the Truth: and with a purpoſe to ſubmit unto it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.9.14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.32.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We muſt mak conſcience of the practice of what we know. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.100.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We muſt with diligence attend upon the publick Miniſtrie of the Word, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are the Scriptures divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Into the old and new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is the Old Teſtament divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Into the Law and the Prophets; or Moſes and the Prophets, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.13. Luc. 16.29.31.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth this Diviſion comprehend the whole Old Testament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes For by <hi>Moſes</hi> we are to underſtand the five Books of Moſes, which containe the whole Law: and by the <hi>Prophets</hi> we are to underſtand all thoſe Books which the holy Prophets have written as expoſitions of the Law of Moſes. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.23.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether are the books called Apocripha to be received as part of the Old Teſtament, and accounted Canonicall Scripture or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The whole Old Teſtament from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the end of <hi>Malachy</hi> is Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scripture: But the Bookes called <hi>Apocrypha,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170467:8"/>are no part of this ſacred Canon; and therefore they are fitly diſtinguiſhed from the authenticall Bookes of the old Teſtament by this title <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cripha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may this appeare, that theſe Apocryphall Bookes are not to be accounted Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All the Canonicall Books of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were written by Prophets in the Hebrew tongue: But theſe Apocryphall bookes were not penned by Prophets, neither were they written Originally in the Hebrew tongue,</p>
            <p n="2">2. All the Canonicall Bookes of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament were committed to the Jewes and they weare faithfull Regiſters of them. But the Jewes never received theſe Apocryphall bookes as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, never kept them as the Oracles of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many errours and humane frailties are found in theſe Apocriphall Bookes which cannot agree to Bookes indited by the holy Ghoſt. And therefore theſe Bookes are not to be accounted Canonicall. Reade <hi>Tob.</hi> 6.6, 7. &amp; <hi>Tob.</hi> 5.11, 12. <hi>Tob.</hi> 12.15. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.2, 3, 4. 2 <hi>Macc.</hi> 14.37, 41, 42. and 2 <hi>Macc.</hi> 12.43, 44. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 46.20. compared with 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.6. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the number of the Bookes that are to be accounted Canonicall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Canonicall Bookes of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are thirtie nine: the Canonicall Bookes of the New Teſtament are twentie ſeven.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170467:9"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>Why are the Scriptures of the Old, and New Teſtament called Canonicall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they containe the Canon, or Rule of our Faith and life. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the proper Office of this Canon of Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt our Faith muſt be meaſured by this ſacred Canon.</p>
            <p>Secondly all Controverſies in Religion muſt be divided be this Rule of truth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly our life and all our actions muſt be guided by the Canonicall Scripture, as by a ſtraight Line and Rule. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Seeing you affirme Canonicall Scripture to be the Rule of Faith, and the Judge of all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, tell me therefore, how know you that the Scriptures are of infallible truth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Scriptures are the very word of God: and therefore of infallible truth, and divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. They therefore that ground their faith upon Canonicall Scripture, build upon a Rocke, and not upon the ſand. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you the Scriptures to be the very Word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt the Scripture doth teſtifie this of it ſelfe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God. &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Gods own ſpirit, doth teſtifie to the conſciences of his Children, and aſſure them, that the Scriptures are the Oracles of God. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.20, 27.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170467:9"/>
            <p> Thirdly, many Arguments may be drawn out of Canonicall Scriptures, whereby we may, diſcerne theſe Books to be no humane writings but the very word of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are thoſe Arguments, which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a reaſonable man to believe that the Scriptures are the Word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe; Firſt the puritie and divine perfection of the Doctrine contained in Scripture: Here are many ſacred and heavenly Myſteries concerning mens Salvation, which are farre above the reach of humane reaſon, and could never have been found out, had not God revealed them by his Spirit. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. 119.96. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7, 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Scriptures containe many Propheſies of ſuch things as could not be foreſeen in their cauſes: which have been fulfilled in the ſame manner as they were foretold. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13, 14. 49.10. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.2, 3, 5. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.28.45. 1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.11, 12. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Scriptures are of admirable power and efficacy to humble and terrifie the Sinner to comfort the conſcience, and to convent the Soule <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Such is the grace and Majeſtie of the Scriptures, though written in a plaine and eaſie ſtyle as is not to be found in any humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.17, 18, 21, 24.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170467:10"/> 5. The ſweet Harmonie, and perfect concord of every part of Scripture with other: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe Bookes were written by divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in ſundry places at ſundry times.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Antiquitie of the Scriptures above all humane writings. And the admirable preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Book, notwithſtanding the ſtrange ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Satan, and his wicked Inſtruments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The gracious ſimplicity of the Penmen of Scripture, who neither ſpare their friends nor themſelves, but moſt freely and impartially ſet downe their owne faults, and infirmities, as well as others: which had they been guided by humane reaſon, they would never have done.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The conſtant Teſtimonie of many holy Martyrs; and of the Church of Chriſt in all ages.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>You have proved the Scriptures to be the Word of God, and therefore I doubt not but a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may boldly build his Faith upon them: But whether are the Scriptures a ſufficient and perfect Rule of Faith and Obedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, all points of neceſſarie Faith and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe are contained in the written word, and therefore the Scriptures are a ſufficient and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Rule.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by the Contents of Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the Contents of Scripture, we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not only what is expreſſed in ſo many letters and ſyllables, but whatſoever may thence by manifeſt and neceſſary conſequence be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170467:10"/>
            <p> Q. <hi>How may it appeare that the Scriptures are a ſufficient and perfect rule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By theſe Arguments: Firſt, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are able to make a man wiſe to Salvation through Faith in Jeſus Chriſt. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Law and the Goſpell (which are the ſubject matter of Scripture) are both perfect. The Law is ſo perfect a Rule of all to be done that nothing may be added to it or taken from it: <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 32. The Goſpell is ſo perfect a Rule of all things needfull to be believed that nothing may be added to it or taken from it. See <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All that we need to bring us to Salvation is either to be taught, or reproved, or inſtructed, or corrected, or comforted. But all this the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are able to doe, they are able to teach, to reprove, to correct, to inſtruct in all righteouſneſs, and to comfort in all eſtates. Reade 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.1, 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.50. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.29, 31. Joh. 5.39. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Lu.</hi> 24.44. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.22, 25. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Scriptures are able to furniſh the man of God (that is the Miniſter) ſufficiently to every dutie of the Miniſtrie, and to make him perfect (whoſe dutie it is to declare the whole Counſell of God to the People) therefore they are much more able to give the people ſufficient Inſtruction Soe 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.27.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Scripture is ſtiled a Rule: now a Rule muſt be fit to meaſure that which is to be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170467:11"/>by it without addition otherwiſe it is no juſt Rule. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What gather you from this Doctrine of the Sufficiency of the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Seeing the Scriptures are a ſufficient, and perfect Rule, therefore we need no unwritten verities no Traditions of men to ſupply any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed defect of the written word of God. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.6, 9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <head>The ſix Principles of <hi>Mr PERKINS</hi> expounded.</head>
            <div n="1" type="principle">
               <head>The firſt Principle.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat doſt thou believe concerning God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is one God, Creator and Governor of all things, diſtinguiſhed into the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>The Expoſition.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What particulars are to be obſerved in this Principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Three things are here ſet downe to be believed concerning God. Firſt the Unitie of the Godhead. 2. The Diſtinction of this one God into three perſons. 3. The workes, whereby God hath made himſelfe known.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How is God One?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In being and Eſſence: the Spirituall Eſſence of God is but one, and no more in number. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4, 5, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170467:11"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>Can you give me any true Definition or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God as he is in himſelfe is known to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe only; and therefore a perfect definition of God cannot be given: but yet he may be deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſufficiently to diſtinguiſh him from all Idols, from all Creatures whatſoever. <hi>Job.</hi> 11.7.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How may God be deſcribed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By his Attributes.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the Attributes of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are thoſe eſſentiall properties which are attributed to God in Scripture, that we may therby the better conceive of his incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Eſſence.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Tell me how may God be deſcribed by his Attributes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus. God is a ſpirit abſolutely perfect, Eternall, Infinite and Immutable. See <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.2, 4. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.6. &amp; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.26, 27. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How elſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus. The Lord is a living God, of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine underſtanding, &amp; will, of infinite power, and infinitely holy, infinitely Juſt, infinitely Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp;c. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.2, 3, 4. &amp; 147.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. <hi>Exodus</hi> 33.19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.35. <hi>Job.</hi> 42.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. &amp; 135.6. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5, 6. &amp; 34.6, 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8, 9.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>How is this one God diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Into the Father, the Sonne and the Holy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170467:12"/>Ghoſt. And theſe three Perſons, or Subſiſtencyes are not three Gods, but one God, having one and the ſame ſimple, and divine Eſſence together. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16, 17. &amp; 28.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.30, 38. &amp; 14.9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Father?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Father is the firſt Perſon in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who by a divine generation hath eternally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten his beloved Sonne of himſelfe. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22, 25. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sonne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſon is the ſecond Perſon, begotten of the Father from all eternitie; who is alſo called the Word, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. &amp; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.18.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt is the third Perſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Father and the Son. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26, and 15.26. and 16.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doe theſe three Perſons differ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They differ not in degree or dignitie, for they are Coequall: <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.17, 18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. But they are diſtinct in order and manner of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting. The Father is a Perſon without beginning, &amp; therefore the firſt in order. <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.17, 18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6.</p>
                  <p>The Son is of the Father alone, and therefore the ſecond perſon in order.</p>
                  <p>The holy Ghoſt is of the Father, and of the Sonne, and therefore the third Perſon in order, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How elſe are theſe three Perſons diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170467:12"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> By their relative and perſonall properties.</p>
                  <p>The relative and perſonall propertie of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is to be unbegotten, and to beget. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p>The relative propertie of the Sonne is to be begotten <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.18.</p>
                  <p>The relative propertie of the Holy Ghoſt is to proceed. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the workes whereby God hath made himſelfe known to the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Creation and Providenc; which are uſually attributed to God the Father.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is Creation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Creation is the firſt outward worke of God whereby of nothing he made all things very good. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>With what inſtrument did God make the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God uſed no other Inſtrument, but his word. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3, 8, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6.9. &amp; 148.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How long did God continue working before this great worke was finiſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Six dayes.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>To what end did God make the world?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the communication of his goodneſſe; and the manifeſtation of his Glory. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is Providence?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Providence is the ſecond outward worke of God whereby he preſerveth and governeth all the Creatures he hath made, and provideth for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170467:13"/>every one of them. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.25. and 245.25, 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. and 5.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q Doth the Providence and Government of God extend to all things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes, there is not any creature, there is not any thing belonging to any creature but comes under the hand of Gods government, and under the eye of his Providence. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.25. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17. and 4.6, 7, 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.9. <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.6, 7.24, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q How doth God provide for his Creatures?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Ordinarily God provideth for them by ordinarie meanes and this is ſtiled Gods ordinarie Providence. Sometimes God provideth for them extraordinarily and by miracle; and this is called his extraordinarie Providence. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147 8, 9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.21, 22. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13, 14, 15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.21, 22. and 34, 28. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.20, 21. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.4, 6. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="principle">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170467:13"/>
               <head>The ſecond PRINCIPLE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat doſt thou believe concerning Man, and concerning thine own ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All men are wholly corrupted with ſinne through Adams fall, and ſo are become ſlaves of Satan, and guiltie of eternall damnation.</p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>The Expoſition.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Summe of this Principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The eſtate of Man as he is fallen, is here expreſſed. all men by nature are ſinfull and miſerable.</p>
                  <p>The eſtate of Man by creation is here imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for Adams fall doth imply a good and happie eſtate, from which he fell.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What was Adam?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt man that God made, and the common Root of Mankind.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What was the estate wherein Adam was created, and from which he fell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Adam was made in the Image, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God a moſt excellent and happie Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And ſuch as was the eſtate of Adam, ſuch ſhould have been the eſtate of all his poſteritie, if he had not fallen. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Seeing man was created in the image of God, tell me wherein did this image conſiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170467:14"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> It conſiſted chiefly in thoſe excellent gifts and habits of Wiſdome, Holineſſe, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which God beſtowed upon Man, whereby man was able in a Spirituall manner to reſemble the Wiſedome, Holineſſe, &amp; Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God his Creator. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How did Adam looſe his Originall Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe that God beſtowed on him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By his diſobedience, in eating the fruit of that tree, whereof God had expreſsly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, that he ſhould not eate <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What tree was it, the fruit whereof was forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The tree of knowledge of good and evill. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Was this tranſgreſſion of Adam the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of all men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes, Adam was the common Root of Mankind all men were in his loynes, &amp; therefore <hi>in Adam all have ſinned. Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9, 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the eſtate of man by nature ſince the fall of Adam?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> All men are by nature the children of wrath being dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1, 3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Sinne is the Tranſgreſſion or breach of the Law of God. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How many ſorts of ſinns are there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two: Originall Corruption, Actuall Tranſgreſſions.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170467:14"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Q. What particulars are needfull to be known concerning Originall ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe foure: firſt the parts whereof it conſiſteth: ſecondly, the parties corrupted, and infected with it; thirdly, the Extent of it; 4ly the outward Efficient cauſe of it: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the three latter are expreſſed in this Principle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What are the parts of Originall ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The parts whereof it conſiſteth are two: the privation and abſence of Originall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and the contrarie habit of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, or an indiſpoſition to good, and an inclination, and proneneſſe to all manner of evill. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. and 8.21.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What parties are infected with Originall ſin?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All men whatſoever, that deſcend from Adam by ordinarie generation: no creature begotten of Adam is exempted from this corruption. Such as the Roote is ſuch will the branches be: like egge, like bird. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19 &amp; 5.12. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the extent of it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Originall corruption is the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole man; all the powers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoule, and all the members of the body are infected with it. The minde is vaine, and fleſhly: the underſtanding darke and blinde. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.16. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                  <p>The Conſcience is defiled, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</p>
                  <p>The will is perverſe obſtinate and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.16.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170467:15"/>
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17.</p>
                  <p>The affections are unruly, and diſordered. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.19.</p>
                  <p>And all the members of the body are the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Inſtruments of the ſoule for the execution of ſinne. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13, 19.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Whence cometh this Originall ſinne? what is the Efficient cauſe of it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The tranſgreſſion, and diſobedience of Adam. <hi>By one man ſinne entred into the world, Rom.</hi> 5.12, 19. All men were in Adams loynes, when he ſinned; and therefore all men being equally guilty of Adams Tranſgreſſion, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually infected with Originall ſinne from the womb. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 58.3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the fruits, that Originall ſinne bringeth forth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All actuall ſinnes: Evill thoughts in the mind; inordinate affections in the heart; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſpeeches, and wicked deeds are as ſtreams, that flow continually from this impure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, this ſink, and puddle of Originall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence. <hi>Gen:</hi> 6.5. <hi>Mar:</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Puniſhment, that every ſinne deſerveth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The curſe of God. <hi>Curſed is every one, that continueth not in all things, which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the book of the law to do them,</hi> Gal. 3.10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts, and branches of this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe, viz. 1. Spirituall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170467:15"/>under Sathan. All men by nature are ſlaves of Sathan, to whom they have voluntarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled themſelves. Satan raigneth in the hearts of naturall men, and they willingly acknowledge him to be their Prince, by doing his will, living under his lawes and delighting in his workes of darkneſs. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.34.44. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Temporall calamities, and Judgements innumerable. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Temporall death which is the Separation of the ſoule from the body <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. &amp; 5.12.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Eternall death and Damnation in Hell. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6, 13. Mar. 16.16.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is Hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a place prepared of God for the eternall puniſhment of the wicked, both Angels &amp; Men: where the worme dieth not and the fire is not quenched, where the torments are both endleſſe and eaſeleſs. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. <hi>Mar.</hi> 943.48.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Doth every ſinne deſerve eternall death?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes; every ſin being committed againſt an infinite God, deſerveth eternall puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When ſhall ſinners be caſt into Hell?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſoules of the wicked when they goe out of their bodies are ſent immediately to Hell, where they are kept impriſoned untill the day of Judgement: &amp; then theſe bodies ſhall be joyned to their ſoules, &amp; both together ſhall be caſt into hell fire; as they ſinned together on earth ſo they ſhall ſuffer together in hell everlaſtingly. <hi>Lu.</hi> 16.22, 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="principle">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170467:16"/>
               <head>The Third PRINCIPLE.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat meanes is left for thee to eſcape this damnable eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the eternall Sonne of God, being made man, by his death upon the Croſſe, and by his righteouſneſſe, hath perfectly alone by himſelfe accompliſhed all things that are needfull for the ſalvation of man.</p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>The Expoſition.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſumme of this Principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Principle containeth the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Doctrine of perfect Salvation by Chriſt, which is the ſumme of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of this principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are principally two,</p>
                  <p>Firſt the Author of Salvation, the perſon of the Redeemer is here deſcribed.</p>
                  <p>Secondly the great worke of Redemption is expounded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Who is the Redeemer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why is the Redeemer called Jeſus?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus is the proper name of the Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and it ſignifieth a Saviour. The Redeemer was called Jeſus, becauſe <hi>he was to ſave his people from their ſinnes, Mat.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170467:16"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>Why is the Redeemer called Christ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As Jeſus is the proper name of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, ſo Chriſt is the name of his office, and it ſigniſieth <hi>one annointed.</hi> The Redeemer, was called Chriſt, or <hi>Meſsias,</hi> becauſe he was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anointed of God that he might be a fit <hi>(a)</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and <hi>(b)</hi> Prieſt, and <hi>(c)</hi> King to his Iſrael. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.25. (a) <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. and 24.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. and 21.11. (b) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.5, 6. (c) <hi>Pſal</hi> 45.6, 7. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.32, 33.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How was the Redeemer annointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of God was powred upon him without meaſure: <hi>God annointed him with the holy Ghost and power: Act.</hi> 10 38. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7, 8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.34. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 61.1. <hi>Lu.</hi> 4 18.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth the Propheticall office of Chriſt conſiſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Propheticall office of Chriſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in revealing to the Church the whole will of his Father: even all things neceſſarie to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Math.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.15.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt is the great Doctor of the Church, who teacheth his Diſciples, outwardly by his Word, and inwardly by his Spirit. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8, 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Wherein conſiſteth the Priſthood of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It conſiſteth chiefly in offering himſelfe a propitiatory ſacrifice to his Father, to the end he might fully ſatisfie the Juſtice of God for our ſinnes, and ſo might reconcile us unto his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170467:17"/>Father. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2. &amp; 4.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 26.</p>
                  <p>To this ſatisfaction which Chriſt made to the Juſtice of God, while he was upon earth, we may add the perpetuall interceſſion, which he maketh for us now in Heaven. And ſo the parts of his Prieſthood are two. <hi>Expiation</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. Rom.</hi> 8 34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24, 25. &amp; 9.24.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth the Kingdome of Chriſt conſiſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. In the Collection of his Church, &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering his ſubjects out of the world <hi>Act.</hi> 15.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the protection, &amp; peaceable government of his Church in the world: in the defending his ſubjects and ſubduing his and their enemies. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1, 2. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In rewarding his ſubjects and puniſhing his enemies in the world to come. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.33, 34, 41, 46. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28.29.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What kind of perſon is Chriſt the Redeemer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt is the eternall Sonne of God made man, that is, God and man in one perſon. Hence he was called <hi>Immanuel,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>God with us. Mat.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 7.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Tell me more particularly, what is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the perſon of Chriſt the Redeemer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> His two natures divine and humane: and the union of them.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the Divine nature or Godhead of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170467:17"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt is the naturall and only begotten Sonne of God: coeſſentiall, coequall and coeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall with God the Father and God the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14, 18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.30. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.6. <hi>Joh:</hi> 1.1. and 17.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to conceive of the Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or manhood of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Manhood of Chriſt conſiſteth of a reaſonable ſoule, and of a true humane body: &amp; ſubſiſteth in the ſecond perſon of the Deitie. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.38. &amp; 17.5. <hi>Lu.</hi> 24.39. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Was Chriſt like unto Adam, Abraham and other Men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Yes, as he is true God, ſo he is true man. Chriſt our Saviour took to him the ſubſtance, the Eſſentiall properties &amp; the common infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of mans nature: he was like unto us in all things, yet without ſin. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.5. <hi>Joh:</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>Mar:</hi> 11.12, 13. <hi>Heb:</hi> 2.17. &amp; 4.15. &amp; 7.26. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q: How did Chriſt become man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> He was not begotten but was made man. He was conceived of the holy Ghoſt &amp; borne of the Virgin Mary. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.3. <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.4. <hi>Mal:</hi> 1.18.20. <hi>Lu:</hi> 1.30, 31.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How are we to underſtand this, that Chriſt was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus, Chriſt was conceived not of the ſubſtance but of the power of the Holy Ghoſt: the holy Ghoſt by his incomprehenſible power wrought his conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſupernaturally. <hi>Lu:</hi> 1.35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q: How are we to conceive of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of theſe two natures of Christ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170467:18"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> Although Chriſt conſiſt of two Natures, yet he is but one Perſon. The manhood of Chriſt is united immediately to the Perſon of the Sonne, &amp; by the perſon, to the God-head of the Sonne: and ſo the nature aſſuming, and the nature aſſumed, make but one Perſon of the Redeemer, one Chriſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What kind of union is this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A Perſonall union, but not a union of Perſons: a Union of natures not in nature: a Union of two natures in one perſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q: But are not theſe two natures mingled and confounded in Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> No verily; although they be inſeparably united in perſon, yet they remaine ſtill diſtinct in ſubſtance, properties, and actions, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q: Why was it neceſſarie that God and man ſhould be thus united in Christs Perſon?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> It was neceſſarie that Chriſt ſhould be God-man, that he might be a fit Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man; that he might be every way fit both to reconcile God to man, and man to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q: Tell me more particularly why was it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that Chriſt ſhould be Man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It was neceſſarie that Chriſt ſhould be made man; Firſt that the Lord might performe the promiſe, wich was made to Adam in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, <hi>that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170467:18"/>Serpents head, Gen:</hi> 3.15. If Chriſt had not been made of a woman, he could not have been the promiſed Meſſias.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, becauſe our redeemer was to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and dye for us: but God could not ſuffer. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 12.5, 6.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly becauſe it makes moſt for the glorie of Gods juſtice to exact ſatisfaction from that nature, that had ſinned. Man had ſinned and therefore man muſt ſuffer. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14, 16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q: Why was it neceſſarie, that Christ ſhould be God alſo?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. That he might not be ſwallowed up of death, that he might be able to beare the wrath of God, and to conquer and overcome Satan, Death and Hell for us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That his obedience, and ſufferings might be of infinite value and merit. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Hitherto of the perſon of the Redeemer; it remaineth to conſider of the worke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption? Tell me now what kind of worke is this worke of Redemption?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As the Perſon of the Redeemer is <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull; Iſa:</hi> 9.6. ſo the worke of Redemption which he hath wrought for us, is <hi>admirable:</hi> as two diſtinct natures concur to make the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Redeemer: ſo the operations of both theſe natures concur to the effecting of this great worke of Mans Redemption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. How may this admirable worke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption be deſcribed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170467:19"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> Redemption is a moſt gracious, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull deliverance out of the captivity of ſinne, and Satan; and from the curſe of the Law. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Heb:</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How, and with what price hath Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not with ſilver, and gold, but with his precious blood. Chriſt hath redeemed us, by making full ſatisfaction unto the juſtice of God for us. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.7. <hi>Col:</hi> 1.14.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>To whom was the price of Redemption paid?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt paid the price of our Redemption to God his Father. We were captives to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, no otherwiſe, then as Satan is the miniſter of God for the execution of that curſe of the Law, which the juſtice of God hath denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and threatned againſt all ſinners: and therefore Satisfaction was to be made unto God. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How, and by what meanes hath Chriſt made ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God for us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By his voluntary obedience, both active, and paſſive: Chriſt our Surety hath paid all our debts for us, both the principall, and the forfeiture, that ſo we might be freely, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by the active obedience of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The obedienee of his life, performed to the whole Law of God for us: When Chriſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170467:19"/>lived upon earth, <hi>he fulfilled all righteouſneſſe,</hi> which we were to fulfill: he kept every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement exactly, in thought, word, and deed; he perfectly performed the perfect Law of God, in our ſtead: and this is called his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive obedience. <hi>Matt:</hi> 3.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.17. <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Rom:</hi> 5.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.4.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by his paſſive obedience?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the paſſive obedience of Chriſt, we are to underſtand his whole Paſſion, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his Death upon the Croſſe. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What manner of death was that, which Chriſt ſuffered upon the Croſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A curſed death; and a meritorious death.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why do you call it a curſed death?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was not only ignominious, and ſhamefull before men; but alſo accurſed before God: for it is written, <hi>Curſed is every one that hangeth on a tree. Deut:</hi> 21.23. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why did Chriſt ſuffer this kind of death, rather then any other?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To declare that he was made a Curſe for us, to the end that he might redeeme us from the Curſe of the Law.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why do you call the death, that Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered upon the Croſſe, a meritorious death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was the price of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The death of an Ordinary man is a duty, and a debt; but the death of Chriſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170467:20"/>was a ſatisfactorie oblation, and a full price of Redemption. <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 5.2. <hi>Mat:</hi> 20.28. 1 Tim. 2.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What made the death of Chriſt thus meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The infinite dignitie of his perſon. Chriſt who willingly ſuffered death, was not a meere man but God and man in one perſon: and therefore it is ſaid, that God <hi>purchaſed his Church with his own blood.</hi> Hence it is that the death of Chriſt is of infinite value and merit, a price ſufficient for the ranſome of the whole world: for in that the naturall and eternall Son of God ſuffered death it is more, then if all men in the world had ſuffered for ever. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Did Chriſt ſuffer for us the firſt death only?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The whole curſe of the Law due to our ſinnes, was laid upon Chriſt our Suretie; and therefore as Chriſt ſuffered the firſt death for us; ſo he taſted of the ſecond death alſo, he did drink up the bitter cup of his Fathers wrath even the torments of Hell, which made him cry out <hi>My God my God why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me. Mat.</hi> 27.46. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.38, 39.42. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.44. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the fruits and effects of Chriſts death?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the death of Chriſt the wrath of God is appeaſed, the ſinnes of the redeemed are remitted, Satan, Death and Hell are vanquiſhed;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170467:20"/>and conſequently, thoſe that were miſerable captives, are gratiouſly and powerfully deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the hands of all their ſpirituall Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Now thoſe who are thus delivered from the captivitie of Sinne, and Satan here, ſhall have perfect deliverance from all ſinne, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wrath, and miſerie hereafter. Chriſt hath merited perfect and eternall Redemption for us: and therefore we expect a day of full Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.14. and 4.30.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Hath Chriſt left any thing to thoſe that are redeemed by him, to be done, or ſuffered in way of merit, or ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Nothing at all. Chriſt is a moſt abſolute and perfect Redeemer, and Saviour: Chriſt alone hath done and ſuffered all things that are needfull for the Salvation of man; and therefore the glorie of that great worke of Mans Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and Salvation, belongeth to Chriſt alone. The righteouſneſſe, obedience and ſuffrings of Chriſt are no way defective; The ſatisfaction that Chriſt hath made to the Juſtice of God, is abſolutely perfect: now that which is perfect is marred by adding ought unto it. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is required of thoſe that are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by Christ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The redeemed ought to live accoding to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170467:21"/>the will of their Redeemer. See <hi>Luc:</hi> 68.74, 75. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.24.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="principle">
               <head>The fourth PRINCIPLE.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t how mayeſt thou be made partaker of Chriſt, and his benefits?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A man of a contrite, and humble ſpirit, by faith alone apprehending, and applying Chriſt, with all his merits to himſelfe, is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before God, and ſanctified.</p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>The Expoſition.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of this Principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Principle layeth downe theſe three things: 1. The quality, and diſpoſition of the perſon, that ſhall attaine to ſalvation by Chriſt in theſe words, <hi>a man of a contrite and humble ſpirit.</hi> 2. What every one that would be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, muſt do: viz. <hi>by faith apprehend, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Chriſt with all his merits to himſelfe.</hi> 3. The fruits, and benefits, which follow upon our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt, which are two, <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How muſt the ſinner be qualified, that he may be made partaker of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He muſt be humbled, bruiſed, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: This Humiliation, and contrition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the ſinner for Chriſt: before the ſinner
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170467:21"/>be thoroughly humbled, and kindly broken, he is altogether unfit to receive Chriſt. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 57.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66.2. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 61.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why muſt a Sinner be thus humbled, before he can be made partaker of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe every man hath naturally a proude, hard, and ſtony heart: and God will not poure the oyle of his grace, and mercy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any other, but a broken Veſſell; the ſinner therefore muſt have his proud, and hard heart humbled, and broken. Sinners muſt underſtand themſelves to be, what they are indeed by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, before they will be willing to come out of their naturall condition. See <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.12, 13. <hi>Eze.</hi> 11.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 36.26. <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 48.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 147.3. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.12.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth this Humiliation, whereby the ſinner is prepared for Chriſt, conſiſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In ſuch a ſight of Sinne, and ſenſe of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, as drives a man to Gods Mercy, and makes the ſinner, ſeeing no meanes of help in himſelfe, or the creature, flee unto Chriſt. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24, 25.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How is it wrought?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God, by the morall Law, (which is a perfect Rule of righteouſneſſe) diſcovers to the ſinner his ſinne, and the puniſhment of it: and convinceth the ſinner of his miſerable, and wretched condition; and lets him ſee, that it is impoſſible for him to come out of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170467:22"/>by his owne ſtrength, and that it is in vaine to expect help from the Creature. Now when a ſinner is come to a right knowledge of himſelfe, to a true ſight and ſenſe of his vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wretchedneſſe, and ſpirituall wants, then leſt he ſhould be ſwallowed up of deſpaire, the Lord lets the ſinner ſee his divine goodneſſe, and his readineſſe to forgive, and the Mercy that is layd up in Chriſt. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.7. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.9. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.10. <hi>Job:</hi> 33.16, 19. — 23.24. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.22, 24.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What followes hereupon?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the ſinner ſeeth himſelfe to be a bundle of ſinne and miſery: when he ſeeth his ſinne, and the ſtrict Juſtice of God, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning death, and damnation on the one hand, and the great Goodneſſe of God, with the Mercy that is revealed and offered in Chriſt, on the other hand: then he loathes himſelfe, bewailes his ſinne, fleeth unto God for mercy, being willing to take Chriſt upon any termes, upon any conditions. When the heart of the ſinner is thus kindly broken, it is then a fit veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to receive the precious oyle of Gods Mercy. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 36.31. <hi>Zech:</hi> 12.10. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.37. <hi>Jer:</hi> 31.18. <hi>Luc:</hi> 15.18, 19. <hi>Matt:</hi> 11.28. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 61.1. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 42.3. <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 14.3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Are there not degrees of this Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes; but every ſinner muſt be humbled ſo farre as may prepare him, and make him fit to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170467:22"/>receive Chriſt. Now a ſinner is then prepared for Chriſt, when he is convinſed of the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of a Saviour: when he is made ſenſible of ſinne, and miſery, and flexible, and tractable to good; when he is willing to yeeld, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto Chriſt, and diſpoſed to take any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion from Gods hand. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.37. <hi>Act:</hi> 9.6. <hi>Act:</hi> 16.30.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When a ſinner is thus humbled, what muſt he do, that he may be ſaved?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.30, 31. Faith in Chriſt is the only way to life, and ſalvation. <hi>Mar:</hi> 16.16. <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.14, 15, 16. <hi>Joh:</hi> 6.47. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.31. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.17. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 10.9, 10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How doth Faith ſave us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As an Inſtrument applying Chriſt. When we ſay, that Faith ſaveth us, the meaning is, that Chriſt apprehended by faith, doth ſave us. As the hand may be ſaid to feed, and nouriſh the Body: ſo Faith may be ſaid to ſave the Soul. Chriſt is the Saviour of ſinners; and Faith is the hand of the Soul, that layeth hold on Chriſt, and cleaveth to this Saviour. Chriſt is the Treaſure, that doth make us rich; and Faith is the hand wherewith we receive this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Act:</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.24, 25. <hi>Joh:</hi> 1.12.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is it Faith alone that ſaveth the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> True Faith never goeth alone, without other graces, and fruits of the ſanctifying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170467:23"/>but yet Faith onely is it, which as an hand, or inſtrument applying Chriſt doth ſave us. <hi>Galat:</hi> 5.22. <hi>Mark:</hi> 5.36. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.28.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Have all thoſe true faith, who profeſſe to believe in Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: faith is in the mouthes of many, but in the hearts of few. An hiſtoricall faith may be found in many: but a Juſtifying, ſaving Faith, is proper to the elect children of God; and therefore it is ſtiled <hi>the Faith of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3.2. <hi>Joh:</hi> 10.26. <hi>Act:</hi> 13.48. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How may this precious grace be deſcribed, what is Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Faith is a ſpeciall gift of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Believer being convinced of the truth, and goodneſſe of the doctrine of the Goſpell, embraceth the promiſe of ſpeciall mercy in Chriſt, and applyeth Chriſt with all his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to himſelfe. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>It is a ſpeciall gift of God, whereby the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever appropriateth, and applyeth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall promiſe of grace, and mercy in Chriſt, to himſelfe in particular, reſting wholly upon Chriſt for life, and ſalvation. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Cant:</hi> 8.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.11.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Object of Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The generall, and compleate Object of Chriſtian Faith, is the written word, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170467:23"/>whole will of God, revealed unto us in his Word. <hi>Act:</hi> 24.14. <hi>Joh:</hi> 20.31.</p>
                  <p>The ſpeciall, and principall Object of a Juſtifying Faith, is Chriſt crucified, Chriſt promiſed, and offered in the Goſpell; or the Promiſe of ſpeciall grace, and mercy in Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom:</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>Gal:</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. <hi>Mar:</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Joh:</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the proper Subject, or Seate of Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The whole Heart, and Soule. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding being inlightned doth ſee the promiſe of grace revealed in the Goſpell, and doth acknowledge it to be true. The will being effectually inclined by the Spirit of God, gladly receiveth, and embraceth the promiſe of grace as ſweet, and good. <hi>Act:</hi> 8.37. <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.10. <hi>Eph</hi> 1.17, 18. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.15.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are three. <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.13.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>What is the firſt of them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Knowledge. The underſtanding can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yeeld aſſent to that divine truth, which it knoweth not: Faith therefore doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe a diſtinct knowledge of what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to be believed. Although knowledge may be where Faith is not; yet Faith can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, where knowledge goes not before. <hi>Joh:</hi> 6.40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 4.16. <hi>Act:</hi> 16.18.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170467:24"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Aſſent. the Believer in his underſtanding giveth firme, and full Aſſent to whatſoever is revealed, and promiſed in the Goſpell. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.20.21. <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.13.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Affiance. The Believer with his heart embraceth the Promiſe of grace as his own, and caſteth himſelfe wholly upon Chriſt, cleaving to him, truſting in him, and depending upon him for remiſſion of ſinnes, and eternall happineſſe. <hi>Cant:</hi> 6.3. <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.13. <hi>Job:</hi> 19.25. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.12.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>What is the principall Act of a Juſtifying Faith? wherein doth it chiefly conſiſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It conſiſteth chiefly in the particular Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the generall Promiſe of grace: or in Affiance, and Reliance upon Chriſt, when the Soul dependeth wholly, and only upon Chriſt, looking after no other help. <hi>Gal:</hi> 2.20. <hi>Joh:</hi> 20.28. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 22.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.2. <hi>Hab:</hi> 1.12. <hi>Cant:</hi> 8.5.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Seeing that Faith unites the Believer to Chriſt, tell me therefore, what are the fruits, that follow upon this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion? what are the chiefe benefits that every Believer receiveth from Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Juſtification, and Sanctification here: and this Salvation which is begun here, ſhall be perfected in unſpeakable happineſſe, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Glory hereafter. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.30.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170467:24"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What is Juſtification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the Juſtification of a Sinner, we are to underſtand that Action of God, whereby God (beholding the ſinner in Chriſt) ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves, and acquits him from all his ſinnes, pronounceth him righteous, and conſequently accepts him to life everlaſting. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.33. <hi>Act:</hi> 13.39. <hi>Rom:</hi> 2.13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is not a man juſtified before God, by that righteouſneſſe, that is inherent in himſelfe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: we are juſtified in Gods ſight, not by my righteouſneſſe inherent in us, but by the righteouſneſſe, and obedience of Chriſt imputed unto us; and therefore Chriſt is ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the Lord our righteouſneſſe.</hi> As our ſinnes were imputed to Chriſt; ſo Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is imputed to us: as the ſinne, for which Chriſt ſuffered, is inherent in us, not in Chriſt; ſo the righteouſneſſe, whereby we are juſtified, is inherent in Chriſt, not in us. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.21. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.6. <hi>Jer:</hi> 23.6. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.21. <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.4.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But this ſeemes to be an abſurd Doctrine, that a man ſhould be made righteous by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of another. We know a man cannot be wiſe with another mans wiſdome, a man cannot be warme with the cloathes another weareth; and therefore how can, we be made righteous, how can we be juſtified in Gods ſight by that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which is reſident in the Perſon of Chriſt and not in our ſelues?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170467:25"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> Although the righteouſneſſe, whereby we are juſtified, be inherent in the Perſon of Chriſt, and not in us, yet it is not Chriſts alone, but, as it is his, ſo it is ours alſo. Look how the ſinne, and Tranſgreſſion of Adam is made our ſinne, in like manner the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is ours. As the ſinne of Adam was of force to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne us, becauſe we were in his loynes, ſo the righteouſneſſe, and obedience of Chriſt our Surety, is much more availeable to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify us. <hi>Rom:</hi> 5.12, 19.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>In what ſenſe, is the righteouſneſſe of our Saviour Chriſt, ours?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As this righteouſneſſe (whereby we are juſtified before God) is Chriſts properly, and inherently; ſo it is ours truely, and really: both in regard of our right, and intereſt to it; and in regard of the uſe, and fruit of it. <hi>See Gen:</hi> 27.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When is this righteouſneſſe made ours?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> At what time we are effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſpiritually united to Chriſt, and made members of his myſticall Body. For being truly, and really united to Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt our Head is truely, and really made ours. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How is this righteouſnes of Chriſt made ours?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the free gift, and gracious Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of God; and by the Application of Faith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. &amp; 4.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170467:25"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What are the parts of Juſtification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> They are two: Abſolution from ſinne; and Acceptation to life eternall; both which preſuppoſe the imputation of the merits and righteouſneſſe of Chriſt. The forgiveneſſe of our ſinnes, Chriſt merited by his paſſive Obedience our gracious Acceptation and Admittance to eternall life, Chriſt merited by his active obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21, 22. <hi>Rom:</hi> 5.18, 19.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Hitherto of Juſtification: tell me now what is ſanctification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Sanctification is the Conformitie of our nature to the pure nature of God. When of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, we are renewed by the holy Spirit to the Image of our Heavenly Father, and made holy when all vitious qualities are purged out of our hearts in ſome good meaſure, and all gracious habits (which are the ſeeds of a vertuous life) are planted in us, then we are ſaid to be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is the Sanctification of a Chriſtian perfect in this life?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No; although Sanctification be of the whole man; yet the whole man is not fully, and perfectly ſanctifyed. The juſtification of a true Believer is perfect, but his ſanctification is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this life. Here we receive but the firſt fruits of the Spirit: and this Sanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (begun here) encreaſeth daily untill it be fully
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170467:26"/>perfected in the life to come. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of Sanctification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are two: Mortification and Vivifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is Mortification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Mortification is the firſt part of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wherein the old man by the applycation of Chriſt his death, and Buriall, is crucified, and buried in a Chriſtian. <hi>Rom:</hi> 6.3, 4, 6. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.1. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.24.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is Vivification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Vivification is the quickning of one that was dead in ſinne: or a daily riſing to newneſſe of life, by the power and vertue of Chriſt his Reſurrection. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall ſuch as are truly ſanctifyed find in themſelves?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> A ſpirituall battell a continuall conflict between corruption dying, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe riſing, and growing in them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7 <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.17.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Doe not the good workes of the Children of God that are truly ſanctifyed merit at Gods hand eternall life and Salvation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> No verily: the beſt workes, which the children of God performe are no more then due debt; they are no way beneficiall to God; they are no way comparable to the glory that ſhall be revealed; and therefore they cannot
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170467:26"/>Heaven: yea the good works of the holieſt men are ſtained with many imperfections, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the children of God have more cauſe to condemne themſelves for their good workes, then to expect to be juſtified before God, and to be ſaved by them. <hi>Luk:</hi> 17.10. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 16.2. <hi>Job:</hi> 22.2. &amp; 35.7. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.18. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.17. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 64.6. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 143.2. <hi>Job:</hi> 9.15.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>But are not good workes neceſſarie then to Salvation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Although good workes cannot merit heaven, though they cannot juſtifie us is Gods fight: yet they are in their kind, and order ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, I ſay in their kind and order; namely, good workes are neceſſarie, not as cauſes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but as fruits, and inſeperable compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of true faith, and as markes in the way to Heaven. Yea good workes are as the way, that will leade us to the Kingdome of Heaven. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>Seeing the good workes of the beſt children of God are ſtained with imperfections; and ſeeing good workes are not meritorious tell me therefore what encouragement hath a Chriſtian to be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in good workes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Although corruption cleaveth to the beſt of our good workes, yet ſeeing this pollution is taken away by the Interceſſion of Chriſt, and ſo our good workes become acceptable to God in Chriſt Jeſus; the conſideration hereof ſhould make us zealous of good works, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.36, 37,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170467:27"/>38. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Titus</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>Againe, although good workes be not meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, yet there are many good ends, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie uſes of good workes which ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Chriſtians to bring forth the fruits of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; righteouſneſſe, in abundance. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.14.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What are the neceſſarie uſes of good works? What are the ends a Chriſtian may ayme at, in doing good workes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We muſt abound in good workes;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we may glorifie God our Heavenly Father. <hi>Mat:</hi> 5.16. <hi>Joh:</hi> 15.8. <hi>Phil:</hi> 1.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That we may adorne the Goſpell of Chriſt our Lord and Saviour. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.10. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That we may teſtifie our thankfulneſſe to God and to Chriſt, <hi>Rom:</hi> 12.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That we may teſtifie, &amp; manifeſt the truth, &amp; ſinceritie of our faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16, 17. <hi>Jam:</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That we may make our effectuall calling, &amp; election ſure. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.21.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That we may confirme our weake bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.19.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That we may be patterns to others, and excite them to imitate our example. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. That we may winne ſuch as are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted and even provoke them to embrace the truth. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. That we may at leaſt ſtop the mouths of ſuch perſons as cannot be wonne. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="principle">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170467:27"/>
               <head>The fifth PRINCIPLE.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat are the ordinarie and uſuall meanes for obtaining of Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Faith commeth only by preaching of the Word, and increaſeth daily by it, as alſo by the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments and Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>The Expoſition.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of this principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Principle layeth downe two things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt the meane or the inſtrument of getting Faith, <hi>viz. The Word preached.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly the Meanes, whereby faith being once bred in us is nouriſhed ſtrengthned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, which are theſe 4. the ſame <hi>Word preached, the Sacraments and Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is the Word preached the meane or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of begetting and increaſing faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the Word is both the ſeed that breedeth and the milke that feedeth Faith in us. See 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. &amp; 2.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8.14.7. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is it in the power of the Word being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, to worke faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The word is not able of it ſelfe to worke Faith in the heares of it. The Word is not the principall worker of Faith, but a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Inſtrument, whereby the Lord worketh
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170467:28"/>faith in the hearts of his children. The ſame all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie power, which raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, doth create this grace in the ſoule. Hence it is, that although many heare the Word faithfully preached, yet but a few, even the Elect only believe. Se <hi>Act:</hi> 13.48. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.16. <hi>Joh:</hi> 12.37, 38. <hi>Iſa:</hi> 53.1. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19 20. <hi>Mat:</hi> 13.11.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Seeing the Lord is the principall worker of Faith, may not a man expect to have ſaving faith wrought in his heart, without attending upon the Word preached?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No, for the Lord delighteth to worke by his own Meanes: as the Word cannot work Faith without God, ſo God will not worke Faith without it. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.21.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Seeing the word is both the Seed, and the Foode of Faith, tell me therefore how ought wee to heare the word preached, that we may profit by it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Before we come to the publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we muſt prepare our ſelves to goe to the place of Gods preſence. When we are come to the houſe of God, we muſt remember we are in Gods preſence, and behave our ſelves as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. After we have heard the Word, we muſt meditate of that which we have heard, we muſt hide it and lay it up in our hearts and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to practiſe it. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Jam:</hi> 1.22. <hi>Exod:</hi> 3.5. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.10, 11.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170467:28"/>
                     <hi>Eccl:</hi> 5.1. <hi>Act:</hi> 10.33. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.10, 11. <hi>Job:</hi> 22.22. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 119.11. <hi>Luk:</hi> 2.19. and 51. <hi>Heb:</hi> 2.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How are we to prepare our ſelves, before we come to the publike Ordinance?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. We muſt lay aſide whatſoever may bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the profitable hearing of the Word. See <hi>Jam:</hi> 1.21. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Jer:</hi> 4.3. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 33.31.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We muſt conſider what our ſpirituall wants be and how neceſſarie and profitable the Word of God is for the relieving of theſe our wants, that ſo we may get a ſpirituall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to this ſpirituall food of our ſoules: like new borne babes we muſt crye after this milke that we may grow by it. <hi>Jam:</hi> 1.19. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We muſt intreate the Lord to bleſſe this holy ordinance unto us, and to accompanie the outward Miniſtrie of the Word with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward opperation of the Spirit, that ſo the Word may be effectuall to ſave our ſoules. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 119. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How are we to behave our ſelves when we are come to the Houſe of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We muſt acknowledge the Miniſter to be Gods Meſſenger, and Embaſſadour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt here and receive the Word preached, not as the word of man but as the word of God, even as that word, which one day ſhall judge us. <hi>Job.</hi> 33.23. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.48.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170467:29"/>
                  <p> More particularly we muſt heare the word preached,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Not with drowzie and dull eares, but with diligent attention, to the end we may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what we heare and be affected with it. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.2. and 4.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.14. &amp; 8.16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. With due reverence, yea with feare and trembling. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.5, 6. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9.4. &amp; 10.3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. With meekneſſe and abſolute ſubjection of ſpirit, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. With alacritie and conſtancie not depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before the publike exerciſe be ended. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 46.10.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. With an earneſt deſire to attaine and keep the good ſeed of the Word in our hearts: and with a firme purpoſe to bring forth the fruite of it in our lives. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.23.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What other meanes are there which ſerve to the further increaſing of our Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Sacraments and Prayer.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſeale annexed by Gods own hand to the Covenant of Grace. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.10, 11. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.11.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What is the Covenant of Grace?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That eternall Covenant and contract, laid down in the Word, wherein God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed remiſſion of ſinnes, and everlaſting life to all that believe in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. &amp; 17.7, 8.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170467:29"/>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. and 13.38.39. <hi>Joh:</hi> 15, 16. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Act:</hi> 16.30, 31.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How many parts be there in a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two: <hi>the</hi> outward and viſible Signe; and the inward and inviſible Grace, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. and 26.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Of what uſe are the Sacraments, and to what end were they ordained?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Sacraments were ordained,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To be holy Signes and Seales, to ratifie the Covenant, which the Lord hath made with us to confirme our weake Faith in all the gracious promiſes of the ſame. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To be (as it were) badges of our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby we may be known to be the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17.21.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To be monuments to put us often in mind &amp; remembrance of Chriſt and (as it were) glaſſes wherein we may ſee Chriſt crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes: and therefore the Sacraments are truly called a <hi>viſible word. Lu:</hi> 22.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two, the one repreſenting our Nativitie or new birth; the other repreſenting our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Education, and growth in Chriſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Have theſe ſacraments been alwaies the ſame?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The inward and ſpirituall part which is Chriſt with all his benefits, hath
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170467:30"/>been alwaies the ſame both under the Law, and under the Goſpell. But the outward, and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſignes have been divers according to the times of Chriſt. Before Chriſt was exhibited in the fleſh, there were but two fixed and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Sacraments: and ſince Chriſts comming in the fleſh there are likewiſe two Sacraments and no more. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. &amp; 10.4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What were the ordinarie Sacraments of the old Testament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Circumciſion and the Paſſeover. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.17.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the Sacraments instituted by Christ in the New Testament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper. Now theſe are anſwerable to the Sacraments of the Old Taſtament; for Baptiſme is come inſtead of Circumciſion; and the Lords Supper inſtead of the Paſſeover. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Lu.</hi> 12.13, 14, 15, 19, 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How doe theſe two Sacraments of the New Teſtament differ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme is the Sacrament of our Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and ingrafting into Chriſt. The Lords Supper is the Sacrament of our ſpirituall nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, and growing up with Chriſt, And therefore Baptiſme is but once uſed of us; but the Lords Supper is often to be celebrated. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170467:30"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>Tell me more particularly what is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme is the firſt Sacrament of the new Teſtament wherein, by the waſhing, or ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our bodies with water <hi>in the Name of the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt,</hi> our Regeneration, or new birth is repreſented and our entrance into Chriſtianity ſealed unto us. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36, 37, 38.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What is the outward and viſible ſigne in Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Water, wherewith the partie baptized is waſhed or ſprinkled. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11, 16. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36, 38.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What doth this water repreſent and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A. The Spirit and the blood of Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.5. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What doth the covering or ſprinkling, and waſhing with water ſignifie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A. Our new birth renovation, and putting on of Chriſt: the waſhing of our ſoules with the blood of Chriſt applyed by his Spirit. The covering of our ſinnes and remiſſion of them, through the imputation of the ſuffrings, and death of Chriſt: and the preſenting of us holy, cleane, and without ſpot in the ſight of God, through the imputation of Chriſts obedience, and righteouſneſſe. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170467:31"/>22.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12, 13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why are we baptized in the name (or into the Name) of the Father and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt? Mat.</hi> 28.29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Hereby is ſignifyed that by baptiſme we are conſecrated to the worſhip and ſervice of the only true God, who being one divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, is diſtinguiſhed into three Perſons, <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> In Baptiſme our Adoption in Chriſt by the Holy Ghoſt is ſealed unto us, and ratifyed, and ſo we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to God the Father. Thus by this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament we are (as it were) enroled amongſt thoſe of the Houſehold of God. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.38. and 19.5. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Gen:</hi> 48.16. <hi>Eph:</hi> 2.19. and 3.15.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What perſons are to be admitted to this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as by the Lawes of Charitie are to be eſteemed within the Covenant of Grace of what Nation, Sexe or age ſoever they be. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6. and 28.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. and 8.27, 36, 37. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.15.33. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. compared with <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When doe ſuch as are baptized in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancie reape the fruit, and feele the effect of their Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> So many of them as live till they come to yeares of diſcretion, when they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170467:31"/>actually believe in Chriſt, and repent of their ſinnes. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, 5, and 15. and 16.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 38. and 8.30, 31. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lords Supper is the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the new Teſtament wherein by the uſe of bread, and wine adminiſtred, and received according to Chriſt his inſtitution, our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall nouriſhment by Chriſt is repreſented, and our continuance, and growth in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie ſealed unto us. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27, 28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24. &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the outward ſignes of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Bread and Wine both which Chriſt hath expreſly commanded to be received of all Communicants, and the Sacramentall actions about theſe elements of Bread &amp; Wine. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.22, 23. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19.20.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What doe theſe elements of Bread and Wine ſignifie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Bodie and Blood of Chriſt which are exhibited and given to the faithfull, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of them after a ſpirituall and viſible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yet verily and truly. <hi>Mat:</hi> 26.26, 28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25. <hi>Joh:</hi> 6.27, 28, 51. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Tell me more plainly and diſtinctly, How doth the worthy Communicant receive the Bodie, and Blood of Chriſt in this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170467:32"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> As with the hand of the body we receive the Creatures of bread, and Wine, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and ſtrengthen our bodies: ſo Faith is that hand of the Soule, whereby we receive the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, &amp; Blood of Chriſt. The worthy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant by the exerciſe of his Faith, feedeth (as it were) upon Chriſt, and his merits to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall refection, and nouriſhment of his Soule. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.35. <hi>&amp;</hi> 50, 51, 54, 55, 56, <hi>&amp;</hi> 63.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the Sacramentall Actions about theſe Elements of Bread and Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Sacramentall Actions of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter are chieſly three.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt of them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Sanctification, or Conſecration of the Bread and Wine.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth this Conſecration of the Bread and Wine conſiſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Miniſter reciteth the Ordination and Inſtitution of Chriſt, that ſo our faith may have what to lay hold of: he ſanctifieth &amp; bleſſeth theſe creatures of Bread, and Wine by ſolemne Prayer, and Thankſgiving unto God: and theſe Elements being thus ſeperated to an holy uſe, and being adminiſtred, and received according to Chriſt his Inſtitution, become effectuall Signes and Seales of the true, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body &amp; Blood of Chriſt. Thus the Bread, and Wine are conſecrated. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24 &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.22, 23. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170467:32"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>Are not the Bread and Wine by this Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration changed into the Subſtance of the naturall bodie and blood of Christ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No truly: after the Conſecration of the Bread and Wine, theſe Elements are not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Subſtance but in their uſe only: they are ſet a part to an holy uſe, they are now lively Signes and effectuall ſeales, of the Bodie and Blood of Chriſt; but yet they continue in nature and ſubſtance Bread and Wine ſtill. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond Sacramentall Action?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The breaking of the bread and powring out of the wine. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is ſignified hereby?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The crucifying of Chriſt upon the Croſſe: that the body of Chriſt was broken, that the blood of Chriſt was ſhed for us. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28. <hi>Mar:</hi> 14.24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.20.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But it is written, A bone of him ſhall not be broken: How therefore can the breaking of the bread ſignifie that the bodye of Chriſt was broken for us? Joh.</hi> 19.26. <hi>Exod:</hi> 12.46.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Although the legs of Chriſt were not broken, yet the bodie of Chriſt was bruiſed, and even broken with thoſe torments which he ſuffered upon the Croſſe, when Chriſt yeilded up his ſpirit upon the croſſe he was (as it were) rent into two pieces according to his humane
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170467:33"/>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.32, 33. &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.50. <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.37. <hi>Lu.</hi> 23.46. <hi>Joh:</hi> 19.30.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the third Sacramentall Action of the Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The diſtribution and delivering of the Bread &amp; Wine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27. <hi>Mar:</hi> 14.22.23. <hi>Lu.</hi> 22.19.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is ſignified hereby?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That Chriſt offereth himſelfe and his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to all: that Chriſt is given and exhibited to as many as have faith to receive him <hi>Mat.</hi> 26, 27, 28. <hi>Mar:</hi> 14.23, 24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the Sacramentall Actions of the Communicants?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> With reverence to take the Bread at the Miniſters hand, and to eate it: with reverence to take the Cup at the Miniſters hand and to drink of it. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 27. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.23.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>What is ſignified thereby?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The particular Application of Chriſt, and his merits; the feeding (as it were) upon the Bodie and Blood of Chriſt by the exerciſe of a lively faith, to the ſpirituall refreſhing, and ſtrengthening of our inward man. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What Perſons may ſafely come to the Lords Table, and partake of this heavenly banquet?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch as have right and title to this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; and have in ſome good meaſure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared themſelves to partake of ſo holy an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 28.</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170467:33"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What Perſons have right, and title to this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All the true Children of God, and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, that have been baptized, and (being come to yeares of diſcretion) are alſo to examine themſelves, and to trie their fitneſſe for this Sacrament. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.12.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How may a Chriſtian try his fitneſſe for this Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A man muſt ſearch and try, whether he can find in himſelfe thoſe Sacramentall graces which are neceſſarily required in every worthy Communicant.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are they?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They are chiefly theſe: Repentance, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Faith, and Love.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why is Repentance required in every wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communicant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No man may preſume to come to the Lords Table with defiled hands, and polluted feet; now every ſinne defiles, and pollutes the ſoule in Gods ſight; and therefore whenſoever we come to the Lords Table, we muſt remove our ſinnes by a ſolemne renewing of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. <hi>Num.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Jude verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How may this be done?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That we may remove our ſinnes by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne renewing of our Repentance, foure things are requiſite.</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170467:34"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What is the firſt of them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We muſt ſearch, and examine our hearts, and lives thoroughly by the Law of God, to the end we may come to a true ſight of our ſinnes. <hi>Lam:</hi> 3.40. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 119.59. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.7. <hi>Jam:</hi> 1.23.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we have found out our ſinnes, we muſt get mournefull ſpirits, broken, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite hearts for them: we muſt mourne for them with a godly ſorrow. See 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. <hi>Jam:</hi> 4.8, 9. <hi>Joel:</hi> 2.13. <hi>Zech:</hi> 12.10. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51.16, 17. <hi>Jer:</hi> 31.18. <hi>Mar:</hi> 14.72. <hi>Luck:</hi> 7.38.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>What is the third?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we are truely humbled for our ſinnes, we muſt make an ingenuous, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Confeſſion of them to God our Father; we muſt Judge our ſelves for them; we muſt flee to the Throne of Grace, and implore mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey and forgiveneſſe. <hi>Prov:</hi> 28.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 32.3, 4, 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.14. <hi>Ezr:</hi> 9.6, 14. <hi>&amp; Neh:</hi> 1.6, 7. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.31. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51.1. <hi>&amp; Pſal.</hi> 130.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We muſt promiſe, and covenant to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our ſinnes, and firmely reſolve to reforme our waies for the time to come. <hi>Prov:</hi> 28.13. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 1.15, 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 55.7. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.116.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But every one is ready to ſay, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170467:34"/>of his ſinnes: tell me therefore, how may a Chriſtian know, whether his repentance be ſound, and hearty, or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Sound Repentance conſiſteth in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward change of the heart, and affections; and an outward change of the life, and actions; and therefore, if we find this double change in our ſelves; if we find in our ſelves, a true hatred of all ſinne, and an unfained love of God, and goodneſſe, with an earneſt deſire of univerſall Reformation; if we have renounced the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of every groſſe ſinne, and allow not the leaſt infirmity we ſee in our ſelves; then we may conclude our Repentance to be ſound, and hearty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.97, 113. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5, 6, 101, 112. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.18, 19. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, 16, 19.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>Why is Knowledge required in every wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communicant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe the other Sacramentall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces preſuppoſe Knowledge.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, becauſe the Adminiſtration, and Receiving of this Sacrament, is a publike, and ſolemne part of Gods worſhip, wherein many ſacred duties are joyned together; now know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is a grace that is needfull to guide a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the performance of every Chriſtian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and therefore this that is ſo great, and weighty a Duty can never be performed aright, without a good meaſure of knowledge.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170467:35"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What knowledge is required in every wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communicant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That a Chriſtian may be fit to receive this Sacrament,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He muſt have a competent knowledge of the common grounds, &amp; principles of Chriſtian Religion. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He muſt underſtand the doctrine of the Sacraments in generall; and have a diſtinct knowledge of this Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why is Faith required in every worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe this Sacrament was ordained to be a ſpirituall meanes to confirme &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our weake faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe Chriſt and his ſaving benefits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be received without Faith, whoſoever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth to come to this Sacrament without Chriſt. <hi>Joh</hi> 1.12. <hi>Ephoſ.</hi> 3.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. What kind of Faith is required in a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiver?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That kind of Faith which maketh a true Believer, will alſo make a worthy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant: now that is, not an Hyſtoricall but Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying a particular Faith; ſuch a faith as giveth firme and particular aſſent to the truth of this Propoſition <hi>Chriſt loved me and gave himſelfe for me, Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Joh:</hi> 20.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.1.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170467:35"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Q. What is the office of Faith in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To behold and to receive Chriſt, and to feed upon the Body and Blood of Chriſt. For Faith is that ſpirituall eye, whereby the true Believer ſeeth Chriſt and diſcerneth the Lords Bodie and that hand of the ſoule, whereby the true Believer receiveth Chriſt: and that mouth of the ſoule whereby the true Believer feedeth upon the Bodie and Blood of Chriſt in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.56. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Joh:</hi> 1.12. <hi>Joh:</hi> 6.35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Why is love required in every worthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe Chriſt provided this Heavenly banquet not for ſtrangers but for thoſe of his own Family, for his own Diſciples. Now mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all love, &amp; Charitie is the Cognizance of a true Diſciple, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.35. 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.14. and 4.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe we cannot upon good ground ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to have the forgiveneſſe of all our ſinnes ſealed up unto us in this Sacrament except we bring Chriſtian Charitie in our hearts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.14, 15. and 18.35. <hi>Mar:</hi> 11.25.26. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 37.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe this Sacrament was ordained to be a ſeale, as of our union with Chriſt our head, ſo of our Communion with all the true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Becauſe Charitie is the Rule of all graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170467:36"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What rules of love are we to obſerve when we intend to come to the Lords Table?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe two Rules (preſcribed by Chriſt) are diligently to be obſerved, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. If he hath ought againſt thy neighbour, if thy neibour have offended, and wronged thee, forgive him. <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.25. <hi>Mat:</hi> 5.44. <hi>Luk:</hi> 6.27, 28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.21.22.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If thy brother hath ought againſt thee, if thou haſt any way offended, grieved or wronged thy brother, goe &amp; reconcile thy ſelfe unto him &amp; then come to the Lords Table. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Hitherto of the Sacraments; tell me now, what is Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Prayer is a pious Colloquy, and humble Diſcourſe with God; wherein we lift up our ſoules, and expreſſe the deſires of our hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as to our heavenly Father. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.1. &amp; 62.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6, 9.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How may we expreſſe the deſires of our hearts unto God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord underſtands the language of the heart, as well as of the tongue; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may expreſſe the wiſhes and deſires of our hearts, both by vocall, and by mentall Prayer. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.8.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is mentall Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the expreſſion of the mind by ſecret ejaculations, by ſighes, &amp; groanes. See <hi>Ex.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 79.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170467:36"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What is a vocall Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is the expreſſion of the mind in words; when our tongues are the true interpreters of our hearts, opening and uttering our inward defires unto the Lord. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8: 22, 23. <hi>Joh:</hi> 17.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is there any Rule left us, by which we ought to frame our Prayers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes; the Prayer, which Chriſt taught his Diſciples, commonly called, <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> is both an abſolute Prayer in it ſelfe, which we may, and ought to uſe; and alſo a perfect Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme of Prayer. All our Prayers are to be framed according to this Patterne. <hi>Luk:</hi> 11.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are we generally to conſider, for the right performance of this duty in Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That we may rightly performe this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and heavenly duty, theſe foure things are to be conſidered,
<list>
                        <item>1. To whom we are to pray.</item>
                        <item>2. In whoſe Name.</item>
                        <item>3. In what manner.</item>
                        <item>4. For what perſons.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>To whom are we to pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To God alone. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 38.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 50.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 65.2. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 42.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 48.11. <hi>Phil:</hi> 4.6.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why are we to pray to God alone?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe God only knoweth the hearts of all the children of men. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>Chron:</hi> 6.30. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 44.21. <hi>Jer:</hi> 17.10. <hi>Act:</hi> 1.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170467:37"/> 2. Becauſe God onely is every where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and therefore able to heare the Prayers of all perſons, in all places. <hi>Jer:</hi> 23.23, 24. <hi>Pſ:</hi> 139.7. — 12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe God onely is Almighty, and therefore able to give us, whatſoever we aske. And as he is Almighty, ſo he is moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and therefore moſt ready to grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts. <hi>Job:</hi> 42.2. <hi>Jer:</hi> 32.17. <hi>Gen:</hi> 18.14. <hi>Luk:</hi> 1.37. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 63.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Becauſe we cannot call upon any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, in whom we may not believe, <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.14. Now we are to believe only in God. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth place his faith, and confidence in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Creature, is accurſed. <hi>Jer:</hi> 17.5.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Becauſe no part of divine worſhip is to be communicated to any creature. But Prayer is ſuch a principall part of divine worſhip, that it is often put for the whole Service of God. <hi>Matt:</hi> 4.10. <hi>Iſai:</hi> 42.8. <hi>Jer:</hi> 10.25. <hi>Joel:</hi> 2.32. <hi>Act:</hi> 9.14.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Becauſe Chriſt hath taught us to direct all our Prayers to our heavenly Father: Now there is none, which is <hi>our Father in heaven,</hi> but God alone. <hi>Matt:</hi> 6.9.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>In whoſe name are we to pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In the Name of Chriſt alone. Prayer is a calling upon God the Father, in the Name of the Son, through the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Joh:</hi> 16.23, 26. <hi>Heb:</hi> 4.14, 16. <hi>Zech:</hi> 12.10. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.26. <hi>Eph:</hi> 6.18. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 20.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170467:37"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>Why are wee to pray in the name of Chriſt alone?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1 Becauſe as there is but one God, ſo there is but <hi>one Mediator between God and men, the man Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. Chriſt is the onely Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, as of Redemption ſo alſo of Interceſſion. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3.4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe, we are taught to direct all our Prayers to <hi>our heavenly Father.</hi> Now God is our Father in Chriſt alone: and therefore to come to God in any other name is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>May we direct our prayers to the Sonne or to the holy Ghost by Name?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes prayer may be directed to the <hi>(a)</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or to <hi>(b)</hi> Chriſt his Sonne, or to the <hi>(c)</hi> holy Spirit. But when we direct our Prayer particularly to one perſon of the three, this muſt be done with due care of worſhipping all in one. We muſt pray to all though we name but one: when we mention but one with our mouths, in our minds, and hearts we muſt conjoyne all the three perſons, as thoſe which cannot be ſevered, in will, in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or in outward actions becauſe they are one in nature and Eſſence. <hi>(a) Mat.</hi> 26.39. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14, 16. <hi>(b) Act:</hi> 7.59. and <hi>chap.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>(c) Mat.</hi> 28.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>In what manner are we to pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170467:38"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> We muſt not come raſhly but with prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hearts to the performance of this heavenly dutie. And our hearts being prepared. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.7.108. 1. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1, 2. We muſt pray,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. With heedfull attention, keeping our hearts from vaine and wandring cogitations. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. With humilitie of ſpirit in regard of our owne baſeneſſe and unworthyneſſe <hi>Gen:</hi> 18 27. and 32.10. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.2. <hi>Lu.</hi> 18.13. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18, 19. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9.5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. With reverence towards the glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie of that God, to whom we ſpeak in prayer. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.3, 6. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Luk:</hi> 22.41. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.14.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. With Faith that is with perſwaſion, that our perſons are accepted of God in Chriſt, and that our Prayers ſhall be heard, <hi>Heb:</hi> 10.22. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.15. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. With a ſincere purpoſe to forſake thoſe ſinnes which we confeſſe unto the Lord and pray againſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22. and 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.22.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. With Charitie in our hearts. <hi>We muſt lift up holy hands without wrath and without doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.25.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. With perſeverance without fainting, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently expecting a gratious anſwer from the Lord. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.2. &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>For what perſons are we to pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170467:38"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> For our ſelves and others. For the whole Church of God: for all ſorts and degrees of men; for <hi>(a)</hi> Magiſtrates, <hi>(b)</hi> Miniſters, and the afflicted <hi>(c)</hi> Members of Chriſt. Yea we are to pray for all men living, even our very <hi>(d)</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies who hate and perſecute us. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6.7, 8. <hi>Ioh:</hi> 17.6, 11, 20. <hi>(a)</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.1. <hi>(b) Eph.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.3. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18, 19. <hi>(c) Pſal.</hi> 25.22. and 44.4. <hi>(d) Mat.</hi> 5.44. <hi>Luk:</hi> 23.34. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14.</p>
                  <p>Q <hi>Are none living on earth excepted?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> None but thoſe who have committed the unpardonable finne againſt the holy Ghoſt, and are apparently rejected of God. Se 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.16. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But although all men are to be commended to God in our Prayers, yet are not ſome to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before others?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes; Prayer is one of the moſt principall effects of love; and therefore thoſe, whom we may and ought to preferre before others in our Love, we may; and ought to preferre before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in our Prayers. See <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Eph:</hi> 6.18. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.16, 19. 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 12.23.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts, or ſeverall kinds of Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Petition, and Thankſgiving. Now theſe two are to be joyned together in uſe: and to theſe * Confeſſion of ſinnes is to be anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, that we may be the better prepared both to make Petition and to give thanks, * <hi>Neh.</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170467:39"/>1.6, 7, 8, 9. and 9.32, 33, 34, 35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>Dan:</hi> 9.8, 9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Col:</hi> 4.2. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17.18. <hi>Gen:</hi> 32.9, 11. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.8, 10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Phil:</hi> 1.3, 4. <hi>Col:</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 1.2.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is Petition?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That part of prayer, wherein we requeſt and aske ſomething of God according to his will, revealed in his word. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>With what mind, and affections are we to make our petitions and requeſts known to God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. With a true ſence &amp; feeling of our wants. 1 <hi>King:</hi> 8.38. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. With fervencie of ſpirit, and an earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have our wants ſupplyed. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.1. and 143.6. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.26. and 15.30. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. With ſpeciall faith in thoſe Promiſes which concerne our particular wants. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Iam:</hi> 1.6. and 5.15. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14.15.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>For what things may we make requeſt unto God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For ſuch good things as the Lord hath promiſed our faith muſt reſt upon the promiſe of God: and therefore every petition muſt have reſpect to ſome promiſe. Now as things are promiſed ſo they muſt be praid for; things abſolutely promiſed may be abſolutely prayed for: but where God hath put conditions, and exceptions to his promiſe, here our prayers muſt have reſpect not only to the bleſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: but alſo to the condition annexed:
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170467:39"/>and therefore things conditionally promiſed, muſt be asked with this (or the like) exception, <hi>if it ſeem good unto his Majeſty.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.27, 28, 29. 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 20.7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c. Neh:</hi> 1.8, 9, 11. <hi>Exod:</hi> 32.10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Luk:</hi> 11.13. <hi>Mat:</hi> 26.39. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.10. 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 15.25, 26.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Tell me more particvlarly, what things may lawfully be asked of God in prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt in that perfect patterne of prayer which he hath left us, hath made a briefe col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all ſuch things as are good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be asked in Prayer, and compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them in ſix Petitions: of which the three firſt reſpects Gods glory; the three laſt our own good. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>Luk:</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How are theſe three petitions which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Gods glorie diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt petition concerns Gods glory it ſelfe in theſe words, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name. Mat.</hi> 6.9.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond concerns the meanes of his glory in theſe words <hi>Thy Kingdome come, verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>The third concernes the manifeſtation of it in theſe words, <hi>Thy will be done in earth as it is in Heaven, verſ:</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How are the other three which reſpect our own good diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The fourth petition concerns our bodily life, in theſe words, <hi>Give us this day our daily bread. Mat:</hi> 6.11.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170467:40"/>
                  <p> The other two concerne our ſpirituall life, The fifth our Juſtification in theſe words, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our debts, as we forgive our debtors v:</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>The ſixth our Sanctification in theſe words, <hi>Leade us not into temptation, but deliver us from evill. verſ:</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What is Thankſgiving?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> An humble and heartie acknowledgement of Gods mercies beſtowed on us, and of thoſe particular benefits which we have received from his bountifull hands; rendering unto the Lord due praiſe and aſcribing unto him <hi>Kingdome, Power and glorie for ever.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 20.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 9.1. and 29.2. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 66.1, 2, 3, 8. and 96.7, 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2. and 111.1. <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.5. and 5.20, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.18. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.1, <hi>Mat:</hi> 6.13.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>Having diſtinguiſhed prayer according to the matter thereof; Tell me now what other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions are there of prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Prayer is Publick, or Private: Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie or Extraordinarie.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What is publique Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Publique prayer, is a ſolemne calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, in a publik place, at a publike meeting of the Congregation, where the Paſtor ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the reſt of the Congregation going with him in mind, at the Concluſion ſay, <hi>Amen</hi> to teſtifie their Conſent. 1 <hi>King:</hi> 8.22, 23.55. <hi>&amp;c. Joel:</hi> 2.16, 17. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.15, 16, 19. <hi>Deu.</hi> 27.14, 15. &amp;c. <hi>Neh:</hi> 8.1, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170467:40"/>
                  <p> Q: <hi>What is private Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Private prayer is that, which is made in any private place at any time: as the private prayers of Families: and the * ſecret prayers of particular perſons. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.8. <hi>Luk:</hi> 9.28. <hi>Zech:</hi> 12.12.13, 14. <hi>Act:</hi> 10.30. and 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3.7. * <hi>Mat:</hi> 6.6. <hi>Mark:</hi> 1.35. <hi>Gen:</hi> 25.21.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What is ordinarie prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Ordinarie prayer is that, which is made dayly upon ordinarie occaſions. <hi>Gen:</hi> 24.63. <hi>Dan:</hi> 6.10. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 55.17. and 145.2. <hi>Act:</hi> 10.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is extraordinarie prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A:</hi> Extraordinarie prayer is that, which is made with more then ordinarie fervencie upon ſome ſpecial and extraordinarie occaſion. Unto this kind of Prayer the holy exerciſe of * Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting is often annexed. <hi>Gen:</hi> 32.34. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Ex.</hi> 32.32. <hi>Act:</hi> 12.5. <hi>Lu:</hi> 22.44. <hi>Heb:</hi> 5.7. * <hi>Neh:</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Joel:</hi> 1.14. <hi>Jon.</hi> 3.7, 8. <hi>Lu:</hi> 2.37. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.30, 31.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>What motives are there to excite and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke a Chriſtian to the frequent, and dayly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this dutie of Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Theſe conſiderations following may be ſo many motives to prayer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Chriſt hath taught his Diſciples, how to pray: and the Lord often calleth and inviteth his children to the performance of this dutie: yea God hath commanded that we ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170467:41"/>his ſervice to him <hi>continually,</hi> that is frequently, dayly at ſet times without intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.1, 2. <hi>Mat:</hi> 6.9. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50.15. <hi>Can.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Mat:</hi> 7.7. <hi>Luk:</hi> 18.1. <hi>Eph:</hi> 6.18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.1.8. <hi>Jam:</hi> 5.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Lord hath made many large, and gracious promiſes to thoſe that call upon his Name. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10. and 65.24. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.12, 13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As the moſt compendious way for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to get any thing is to goe to their Parents, and begge it of them; ſo the readie way to obtaine any bleſſing, temporall, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, is to goe to our Heavenly Father, and by humble prayer to begge it, of him. Prayer is the key to open the ſtorehouſe of all Gods treaſures; and (as it were) the only hook whereby we reach all the bleſſings of God, which otherwiſe would be out of our reach. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.9.10, 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18, 19. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.23.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There is no exerciſe a Chriſtian can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme on earth ſo heavenly as prayer. It is no ſmall priviledge that God in his Word vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth to ſpeake to man. But this is a greater priviledge, that the Saints by prayer have free acceſſe to the Throne of grace, and talke with God (as it were) <hi>face to face;</hi> Hence prayer is ſaid to be a familiar conference with God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170467:41"/> 5. Prayer doth ſanctifye all Gods creatures to our uſe: and without prayer the uſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of all things we have is unlawfull: to lay our hands upon any thing that is Gods (whoſe all things are) without asking them at his hand is a ſpirituall kind of felonie. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Mat:</hi> 14.19. and 15.36.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The neglect of this dutie doth expoſe a man to the judgements of God and to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations of Sathan daily. The Saints by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayer run unto God as ſtrong Tower, and commit themſelves to his protection: and ſo the Lord is an hiding place unto them. Without prayer, a Chriſtian Souldier is not able to wield, and uſe that ſpirituall armour aright, which we are commanded to put on for our ſafegard and defence againſt the ſpirituall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of our ſpirituall enemies. Se <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13, 18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.6. <hi>Jer:</hi> 10.25. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 18.2, 3, 6. and 27.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1, 2, 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.4.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="principle">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170467:42"/>
               <head>The ſixth PRINCIPLE.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat is the eſtate of all men after death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>All men ſhall riſe againe with their own bodies to the last judgement: which being ended, the Godly ſhall poſſeſſe the Kingdome of heaven: but unbeliever; and reprobates ſhall be in hell, tormented with the divell and his Angels for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>The Expoſition.</head>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are the Parts of this Principle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In this Principle three things are laid down, which every Chriſtian ought to believe:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the generall Reſurrection of our bodies at the laſt day. <hi>Joh:</hi> 11.24. <hi>Act:</hi> 24.15.</p>
                  <p>Secondly the end of this generall reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that all men may come to judgement. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.10.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly what ſhall fall after the generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; and the generall Judgement; <hi>viz.</hi> the definitive Sentence of Chriſt, both touching the everlaſting Salvation of the Godly, and the eternall Damnation of the wicked, ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted upon them. <hi>Mat:</hi> 25.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When the ſoules of the Godly are ſeparated from their bodies by death: what eſtate ſhall they be in, till the Reſurrection at the last day?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170467:42"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the godly die their ſoules are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried immediately <hi>by the Angels into Abrahams bofome:</hi> and their bodies ſhall reſt in their graves, as perfumed Beddes, till the laſt day <hi>Lu:</hi> 16.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2. <hi>Act:</hi> 7.60. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13, 14.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>When the ſoules of the wicked are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their bodies by death, what estate ſhall they be in, till the reſurection at the laſt day?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the wicked die, their Soules are ſent immediately to Hell; and their Bodies are carryed to the darke Dungeon of the Grave, where they ſhall be reſerved unto the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great day. <hi>Luk:</hi> 16.22, 23. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 49.14.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is it not a thing incredible, that thoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which have been dead many hundred yeares, ſhould be raiſed out of the duſt, and live againe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Why is it not as credible to think that God can raiſe up and bring againe all thoſe bodies that have been, as to be perſwaded, that he can create new bodies, that never, yet had being? The ſame Almightie God who gave life to all living creatures, who gave being to all things out of nothing, is likewiſe able to reſtore life: the ſame God who formed mans bodie of the duſt of the ground, is able to quicken our dead bodies though returned to duſt, and to make them live againe. God hath ſpoken it that the dead ſhall be raiſed out of the duſt; and his power can ſubdue all things to it ſelfe: Now theſe two are the props of our Chriſtian
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170467:43"/>faith in this point <hi>Act:</hi> 26.8. <hi>Gen:</hi> 2.7. &amp; 3.19. <hi>Dan:</hi> 12.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.31, 32. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.23, 29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. When ſhall the generall reſurrection be?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> At the Glorious coming of Chriſt to Judgement: when the world ſhall be deſolved and deſtroyed with fire; and the heavens and the earth ſhall be renewed, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3.7, 10, 12, 13.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall the dead be raiſed up and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the mighty voice of Chriſt: and by the miniſtrie of Angels, Chriſt <hi>ſhall ſend his Angels with a great ſound of a trumpet, and they ſhall gather together the elect, from one end of Heaven to the other:</hi> At the ſound of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet the dead ſhall riſe againe, everie one with his owne bodie: and as many as ſhall then be living, ſhall be changed ſuddenly in the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.49. and 24.31. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.51.52. <hi>Job.</hi> 19.25, 26, 27. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>But ſhall all men riſe againe, both good, and bad?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes; all both good &amp; bad ſhall riſe againe at the laſt day, but not by the ſame Cauſe; nor to the ſame End: For the godly ſhall riſe by the vertue of Chriſts reſurrection, to receive eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. But the wicked ſhall riſe by the power of Chriſt to be judged &amp; condemned. <hi>Act:</hi> 24.15. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28, 29.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170467:43"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>Expreſſe this more particularly. What is the true cauſe of the Reſurrection of the godly?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The godly ſhall be raiſed up by Chriſt as their head and Saviour. In the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, by reaſon of that myſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction which is between Chriſt and the faithfull, divine, and quickning vertue ſhall flow from Chriſt to the Elect and cauſe them to riſe againe from the grave. That Union which is between Chriſt, and all true believers, ſhall even force the grave to render up the bodies of the Saints: for the Head, will not be without the Members. <hi>Joh:</hi> 15.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20, 21, 22, 23, 45. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.52, 53. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>To what end ſhall the bodies of the Saints be raiſed out of the duſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the Saints may be glorifyed in their Bodies as well as in their Soules. As the Soules, and Bodies of the Saints have been Companions in well-doing here; ſo they ſhall be Companions in glorie hereafter. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.42, 43, 44, 49. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the true cauſe of the Reſurrection of the wicked?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The wicked ſhall be raiſed up by the powerfull voice and command of Chriſt the Judge of all fleſh; and by vertue of that Curſe wherein God threatned eternall death to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170467:44"/>our firſt Parents and to their poſteritie) upon their diſobedience; which curſe ſhall certainly be executed upon all unbelievers, and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinners that have noe part in Chriſt, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 5.28. <hi>Gen:</hi> 2.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. To what end ſhall the bodies of the wicked be raiſed out of the duſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That their bodies may partake with their ſoules in the puniſhment of ſinne. As the ſoules, and bodies of the wicked have been partners, and companions in evill doing; ſo they ſhall be companions in Judgement, and torment: as they have ſinned together here, ſo they ſhall ſuffer together everlaſtingly hereafter, <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.29. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>Seing the end of the generall Reſurrection, is that all men may come to Judgement, tell me therefore, who ſhall he the Judge?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt is appointed of God to be the Judge of quick and dead. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.29. <hi>Act:</hi> 17.31. <hi>Rom:</hi> 2.16. and 14.10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ:</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>Q: <hi>How and in what manner ſhall Chriſt come to Judgement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As the firſt comming of Chriſt was in meekneſſe &amp; humilitie; ſo his ſecond comming ſhall be in Majeſtie and glory. He ſhall come in the cloudes of Heaven with power, and great glorie; armed with flaming fire; attended with an innumerable companie of mightite Angels: by whoſe miniſtrie (as the dead ſhall
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170467:44"/>be raiſed, ſo) all men ſhall be cited, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appeare before the Judgement Seate of Chriſt. <hi>Mat:</hi> 12.18, 19, 20. <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.7. <hi>Mat:</hi> 24.30. and 25.31. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.9, 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9.10. <hi>Jude</hi> 14.15. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When the dead are raiſed, and all men ſummoned to appeare before Chriſt, the ſupreame Iudge, then how ſhall they be ranged and ſorted?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As the Shepheard when the Evening cometh gathereth his flocks, and ſeparateth the ſheep from the Goates: ſo in the Evening of the World, Chriſt the good, Shepheard ſhall divide the whole world into two flocks, ſhall ſeparate the good from the bad: the ſheep, that is the Godly he ſhall ſet on his right hand; but the goates that is, the wicked on the left. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.32, 33.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. When the whole world ſhall be arraigned before the Tribunall of Chriſt, then how ſhall every man be tryed and jndged?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All men ſhall be judged according to their workes, as the plaineſt proofes and moſt evident ſignes of Faith, or infidelitie. <hi>Every one ſhall receive the things done in his bodye, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he hath done whether it be good or bad.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35, 36. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 42.43. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and 22.12.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall all men be examined, and their workes made manifeſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170467:45"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the Books that ſhall be opened. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Dan:</hi> 7.10.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What bookes are they that ſhall be opened?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The book of Gods remembrance; and the book of every mans conſcience. Chriſt the ſupreame Judge, who ſearcheth the hearts of all men, will then bring to light the hidden things of darkneſſe, and will make manifeſt the councells of the hearts: out of the Book of Gods remembrance, the Lord will declare the good deeds of the godly, and the ſinnes of the wicked. Every mans conſcience ſhall be made either to accuſe him or to excuſe him. Now the wicked mans conſcience is like a cloſed or ſealed book, but then it ſhall be ſo touched and (as it were) opened, that he ſhall remember all his particular offences, whereſoever, and whenſoever committed; and the conſcience of every wicked man ſhall be as good as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes to accuſe him, and to condeme him. By theſe two bookes all men ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and the wicked ſhall be convicted. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15, 16.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Is there any other book that ſhall be opened?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the Book of life (wherein the names of all the Elect are written) ſhall be opened; that is, it ſhall then be declared before all the World, who are Elect and who are Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, by the exact ſeparation of the one from the other, and by the definitive Sentence, which
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170467:45"/>ſhall accordingly be executed. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12 <hi>Luk:</hi> 10.20. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.5. and 13.8. and 17.8.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the definitive Sentence of the Judge? and in what order will Chriſt give ſentence?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The definitive Sentence which Chriſt will give is twofold, one for the Godly; another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked. The Elect, and godly ſhall firſt receive the Sentence of Abſolution, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: and then Unbelievers and Reprobates ſhall receive the Sentence of condemnation. <hi>Mat:</hi> 25.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Why ſhall the godly be acquitted and abſolved, before the wicked be condemned?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the godly may be Aſſeſſors with Chriſt in the Judgement to be pronounced, and executed upon the ungodly. The Godly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cleared, ſhall have the dignitie to ſit with Chriſt the Judge of all fleſh, and ſhall approve and applaud his moſt righteous judgement upon the wicked; and ſo after a ſort <hi>ſhall judge the world</hi> with Chriſt. Mat. 19.28. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sentence of abſolution and Salvation which the Godly ſhall receive?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt ſhall ſay to the Godly, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherite the Kingdome prepared for you before the foundation of the world, Mat.</hi> 25.34.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170467:46"/>
                  <p> Q. <hi>What is the Sentence of Condemnation, which the wicked ſhall receive?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt ſhall ſay to the wicked, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Divell and his Angels. Mat.</hi> 25.41.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>When this double ſentence is pronounced, what ſhall follow?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The definitive ſentence being pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſhall be executed immediately. The wicked ſhall preſently be bound and caſt into Hell, where they ſhall ſuffer eternall death &amp; endleſſe miſerie. And then the godly ſhall goe into Heaven where they ſhall live in eternall glory, and enjoy perfect felicitie. <hi>Mat:</hi> 13.41, 42. and <hi>v.</hi> 49, 50. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2, 3.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall be the eſtate of the wicked in Hell? How may we conceive of their future Miſerie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. The wicked ſhall be excluded, and ſhut out of Heaven, and baniſhed from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence of God for ever. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.28. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They ſhall be caſt into utter darkneſſe, where ſhall be nothing but horrour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, ſinne and torment: they ſhall have their portion with the Divill, and his Angels, in a lake of fire, and brimſtone, invented by the infinite wiſedome of God, and kindled by the Juſtice and wrath of God: where eternitie ſhall be added to the extremitie of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; where they ſhall live a dying life; and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170467:46"/>die a living everlaſting death. <hi>Mat:</hi> 8.12. and 22.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.30. <hi>Mat:</hi> 13.42: 50. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.10.11. and 21.8. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 66: 24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Mark;</hi> 9.43, 44. and 48.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall be the eſtate of the godly in heaven? how are we to conceive of their future happineſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The godly ſhall be perfectly free from all ſinne, and Miſerie, and from all ſocietie with the wicked. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. and 32.3, 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Mat:</hi> 13.41.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They ſhall enjoy the ſocietie and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of all the glorious Saints, and Angels: They ſhall be made like unto Chriſt their head in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and happineſſe: they ſhall behold even with their bodily eyes, the glory of Chriſt their Lord and Saviour; and with the eyes of their ſoules, the Father alſo and the holy Ghoſt; yea they ſhall have that perfect communion with the bleſſed Trinitie, wherein conſiſteth perfect felicitie. <hi>Mat:</hi> 8.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22.23. 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.10, 11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 36.9. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Securitie and perpetuitie ſhall be added to the perfection of their happineſſe: In Heaven ſhall be happy ſecuritie and ſecure happineſſe: happy eternity and eternall felicity. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. and 17.15. <hi>Iſa</hi> 66.23. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.9.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>Seeing ſuch ſhall be the Miſerie of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170467:47"/>wicked and ſuch ſhall be the happineſſe of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after the last Judgement, tell me now for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; how may we eſcape this eternall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie? How may we attaine to this eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We muſt learne to know the onely true God as he hath revealed himſelfe in his Word.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We muſt learne to know our ſelves, that we are ſinfull and miſerable by nature.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We muſt learne to know Chriſt, his perſon, his natures, his offices, his ſaving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We muſt be humbled by the Law, that we may be willing to come out of our naturall condition, and may be fit to receive Chriſt tendered unto us in the Goſpell. We muſt make ſure our Union with Chriſt: we muſt by a true and lively Faith depend, and reſt wholly upon the Mercie of God, and Merits of Chriſt for the remiſſion of our ſinnes, and the ſalvation of our ſoules.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. When we are united to Chriſt by a juſtifying faith, and have the ſeed of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſown in our hearts, then we muſt waite upon God in a conſcionable uſe of his holy Ordinances, whereby faith and all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſanctifying ſpirit may be confirmed ſtrengthned and encreaſed in us daily.</p>
                  <p>Finally, Grace is the ſeed, and infancie of Glory: and therefore we muſt be infants in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170467:47"/>Grace, before we can be Heires in Glorie: If we have part in the firſt Reſurrection, if our ſoules be raiſed to a ſpirituall life here: then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly we ſhall be ſharers in the glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the juſt hereafter. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6.</p>
                  <p>There are two degrees of ſpirituall life; the life of Grace and the life of Glorie. If we doe not attaine to the firſt of theſe, we cannot attaine to the Second. We muſt therefore live the life of Grace here, if we defire to live the life of Glory hereafter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170467:48"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX <hi>Wherein theſe four Doctrines (appertaining to the firſt Principle) are more fully expounded</hi> viz.</head>
            <p>The Doctrine of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Attributes of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Bleſſed Trinitie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Creation of the World.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Divine Providence.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>DOCT. I. <hi>The larger Expoſition of the Attributes of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat are the Attributes of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are thoſe eſſentiall Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are attributed to God in Scripture, that we may thereby the better conceive of his incomprehenſible Eſſence.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may ſorts are there of theſe divine Properties?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, the Attributes of God are either Principall and incommunicable; or Secondarie, and communicable.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170467:48"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>What are the principall Attributes of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe; abſolute perfection, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe and Immutabilitie.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why are theſe Attributes ſtiled incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt becauſe they are ſo proper to God, that they are not communicable to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Secondly becauſe they are not only incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable themſelves but make all the other Attributes of God incomunicable alſo.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to co nceive of Gods Perfection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. God hath all excellencies in him in the higheſt degree and whatſoever facultie, Vertue, or propertie is attributed to God, is abſolutely perfect. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. <hi>Mark.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whatſoever excellencies are attributed to God, are in him not by participation, but origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and from himſelfe, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is ſo good, and perfect of himſelfe, that he hath all fullneſſe of delight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment in himſelfe, and needeth nothing out of himſelfe to make him bleſſed, and happie: and therefore he is ſtiled the <hi>Bleſſed God. Mark:</hi> 14.61. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> I. 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of Gods infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is infinite in Eſſence. God hath neither Matter nor forme, which are the prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170467:49"/>limits of Eſſence; and therefore his Eſſence is unlimited, and infinite.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God is infinite in Quantitie and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Here Immenſitie and Ubiquitie are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is infinite in Time: and this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Eternitie.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods Immenſitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a divine Attribute, whereby is noted, that God is without all dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. God meaſureth all things, but cannot himſelfe be meaſured by any thing: He is higher then heaven, deeper then hell, longer then the earth; broader then the Sea. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.12. <hi>Jhb:</hi> 11.8, 9.</p>
               <p>And from this Immenſitie of God flowes his Ubiquitie.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a divine Attribute, whereby is noted that God is without and within all places; no where excluded, no where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. God fils heaven, and earth with his preſence, and the Heaven of Heavens cannot containe him: God is contained only in himſelfe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.1 <hi>Jer:</hi> 23.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is Gods Eternitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a divine Attribute, whereby
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170467:49"/>is noted, that God is before, and after all times: He is the firſt and the laſt without beginning, and without end. God is at all times yet without reſpect of time; for one day is with the Lord as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares as one day. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28. and <hi>chap.</hi> 44.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8, 11. <hi>Job.</hi> 66. <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 90. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2, 4.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>What followes upon Gods Infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His immutabilitie; God is therefore immutable becauſe he is infinite.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods immutabilitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a divine Attribute whereby is noted that God is in no ſort mutable, or changeable, but continues alwaies one, and the ſame without any manner of mutation, alteration, or change whatſoever. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.26, 27. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>What are the other Attributes of God, which you called Secondarie, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe: Life, Underſtanding, Will, Power, Holineſſe, Juſtice, Mercie, Truth, and Fidelitie, with many the like.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>Why are theſe Attributes ſtiled com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170467:50"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we may ſee ſome ſhadowes, and glimpſes of them in men and Angels.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the life of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that divine Facultie, whereby God after an incomprehenſible manner liveth of himſelfe moveth himſelfe to his proper workes, and communicateth life to others. <hi>Deu.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Jer:</hi> 10.10. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.26. <hi>Act:</hi> 14.15. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Dent:</hi> 30.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the underſtanding of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods underſtanding is the ſame with his Knowledge, and wiſedome: it may thus be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: It is that divine Facultie, whereby God knoweth and comprehendeth himſelfe, and all things elſe after a perfect, and divine manner. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.2, 3, 4. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.39. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>Tell me more plainly in what manner doth God underſtand all things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God doth not underſtand all things ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively or by diſcourſe, collecting one thing from another, but he knoweth and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth all things by one ſimple, and eternall act; ſo that all things both paſt, and to come, are preſent before him.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>What is the will of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that divine Facultie, whereby God moſt freely approveth, or diſapproveth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he knoweth; and willeth whatſoever
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170467:50"/>may make for his owne glory. And this will of God is the firſt, and higheſt cauſe of all things: See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25, 26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doth not God therefore will a thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, Gods will is the rule of all Goodneſs, and Juſtice: becauſe God willeth this, or that, therefore the thing is good, and juſt; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is good, and juſt, therefore he willeth it. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.35. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the power of God Almighty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods Power, or <hi>Omnipotencie,</hi> is (as it were) the Inſtrument of his will; it is that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine propertie, whereby God is able to doe whatſoever he will, yea whatſoever is ſimply poſſible for ſo perfect an Eſſence. As for thoſe things which imply, and argue imperfection of nature, or imperfection of Grace, it were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable for God to doe them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot doe them. God cannot lye; God cannot denie himſelfe; God cannot die &amp;c. not out of impotency or weakneſſe: but becauſe theſe contradict the perfection of his divine nature. <hi>Job.</hi> 42.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. and 135.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.26. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.37. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2.2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.13. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods holineſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an Attribute, generally noting the vertues of God, and the puritie of his divine
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170467:51"/>Nature. God is ſo perfectly pure from ſinne in himſelfe, that he cannot endure any ſinne in his Creatures. And this Holineſſe of God doth appeare in his Juſtice, Mercie, Truth and other Vertues. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.13 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is his Juſtice?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that divine Attribute whereby God is moſt juſt and Righteous in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and exerciſeth juſtice towards his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as in rewarding and bleſſing them that doe well; ſo in puniſhing them that doe evill. <hi>Deut:</hi> 32.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.137. and 145.17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5.9. and 34.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 10. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6, 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods Mercie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is that divine Propertie whereby God hath compaſſion on them that are in miſerie, though they have offended him, and readie of himſelfe to pardon their offences, and to help them. This Mercie of God appeareth abundantly in his <hi>(a)</hi> Patience <hi>(b)</hi> Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, and <hi>(c)</hi> Bountifullneſſe towards Sinners. <hi>Jud:</hi> 10.16. <hi>Exod:</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8, 9. <hi>&amp;c. Pſalm.</hi> 145.8. <hi>Mic:</hi> 7.18. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>(a) Iſa.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50.21. <hi>Act:</hi> 17.30. <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.25. <hi>(b) Lam.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Joel:</hi> 2.13. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>(c) Mal.</hi> 5.45. <hi>Act.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of Gods Truth, and Faithfullneſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170467:51"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> God hath revealed his will unto us, as it is indeed, and therefore he is ſtiled a God of Truth; and his Word is the Word of Truth. And as the God of Truth cannot lie, ſo he cannot denie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but will certainely performe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he hath decreed, and purpoſed; and this is properly called his Faithfullneſſe. This Truth and Faithfullneſſe of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the conſtant performance of all his Promiſes and Threatnings. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.1. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.43.142. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Joh:</hi> 17.17. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1, 2. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.6.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>Is there any thing elſe to be obſerved, for the right understanding of theſe divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, That we may conceive aright of them, theſe generall Concluſions are further to be obſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Theſe divine properties are attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God Eſſentially. God is Holy, Juſt, and Good without Qualitie; great with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Quantitie; everlaſting without Time; Mercifull without Paſſion: Gods Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Power; Juſtice and Mercie are Himſelfe. God is a moſt pure and ſimple Eſſence; and therefore whatſoever is in God is God himſelfe. Hence it is that God is ſtiled not only juſt, but Juſtice it ſelfe;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170467:52"/>not only mercifull, but mercie it ſelfe, not only the living god but life it ſelfe; &amp;c. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.25. and 14.6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.8. and 5.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The former properties which are ſtiled incommunicable, may be attributed to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which are called communicable: as the wiſedome of God is abſolutely perfect, infinite, eternall and immutable; ſo is his holineſſe; ſo is his Juſtice &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Seing theſe Attributes of God are his Eſſence; and ſeeing they are abſolutely perfect and infinite, therefore it neceſſarily followes, that all thoſe divine properties are equall in God, though they appeare not alwaies equally to us. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <head>DOCT. II. <hi>A larger expoſition of the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinitie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>SEeing the Doctrine of the bleſſed Trinitie, is a deep and incomprehenſible Myſterie, is this Doctrine neceſſarie to be known, and believed of all Chriſtians?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, we profeſſe to believe in God the Father, the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt; and therefore every Chriſtian ought to believe the only true God to be, One moſt pure eſſence, ſubſiſting in three diſtinct Perſons.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170467:52"/>
               <p> Q: <hi>What is a Perſon in the bleſſed Trinitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A:</hi> It is a diſtinct Subſtance having the whole divine Eſſence in it. The moſt pure divine Eſſence conſidered as it ſubſiſts, with his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and incommunicable propertie, is called a Perſon.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may this Myſterie of a Trinitie of Perſons ſubſisting in the unitie of the Godhead, be proved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not by humane reaſon; but by divine Authoritie. The Scripture in divers places maketh expreſſe mention of three Perſons in the Deitie; as 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are three that beare record in heaven the Father the Word and the Holy Ghoſt. Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Goe and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions baptizing them in the Name of the Father and of the Sonne and of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Chriſt was baptized of <hi>John</hi> in Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, the Father ſpake from heaven, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of his Sonne who had then taken upon him the forme of a Servant, and the Holy Ghoſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the likeneſſe of a Dove. This is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully recorded in the foure Evangeliſts. <hi>See Mat.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.10, 11. <hi>Luk:</hi> 3.22. <hi>Ioh</hi> 1.33, 34. By theſe and the like teſtimonies, it is evident that there is a Trinitie of Perſons. in the Deitie. <hi>Reade Joh.</hi> 14.26. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the proper names of theſe three Perſons, or Subſiſtencies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Their proper names are expreſſed in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170467:53"/>thoſe places of Scripture that have been cited.</p>
               <p>The firſt perſon is called the Father.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Perſon is called the Sonne, and the Word.</p>
               <p>The third Perſon is called the Holy Ghoſt, or Spirit.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is the first Perſon called the Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he hath the Relation and reſpect of a Father to the ſecond Perſon.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is the ſecond Perſon called the Sonne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he hath the proper Relation of a Sonne to the firſt Perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Why is the Sonne, and ſecond Perſon called the Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt becauſe as ſpeech is conceived, and begotten of the Mind without any paſſion: in like manner the Sonne is begotten of God the Father. Secondly becauſe he is ſo often ſpoken of and promiſed in the Scriptures, and is (in a manner) the whole ſubject of the Scripture. Thirdly becauſe he bringeth glad tidings from the boſome of the Father: As man doth make known his will to man by his Word, ſo God hath made known, and revealed his will to us by his Sonne. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>Why is the third Perſon called the Spirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although the Father be a Spirit, and the Sonne be a Spirit as well as the third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet this title Spirit is peculiarly attributed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170467:53"/>to the third perſon, becauſe he is (as it were) ſpired or breathed both from the Father, and the Sonne, that is to ſay, He proceedeth from them both.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is the title of holy peculiarly attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the third Perſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although the Father and the Sonne be equally holy with the third Perſon, yet the title of Holy is peculiarly attributed to the Spirit; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is his office to ſanctifie the children of God, and to make them holy: which he doth in a ſpeciall and peculiar manner. The Father and the Sonne ſanctifie immediatly by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: but the Spirit ſanctifieth from the Father, and from the Sonne, by himſelfe immediatly; and therefore he is called the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Father is the firſt Perſon in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, who by a divine generation hath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally begotten his beloved Sonne of himſelfe. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22.25. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Mat:</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sonne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Sonne is the ſecond perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Father from all eternitie. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The holy Ghoſt is the third perſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Father and the Son. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26, &amp; 15.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170467:54"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie of theſe three perſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are one in Being and Eſſence: the Eſſence of the Father is the Eſſence of the Son, and the Eſſence of the holy Ghoſt. Although we may ſay <hi>Perſonally;</hi> the Father is one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, the Sonne is another Subſiſtence; and the holy Ghoſt another Subſiſtence: yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay <hi>Eſſentially;</hi> The Father is one God; the Sonne is another God; and the holy Ghoſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other God: for they are <hi>Coeſſentiall,</hi> that is they have the ſame eſſence together. Although the entire Godhead, the whole divine Eſſence be in each Perſon; yet the three perſons are moſt ſingularly one and the ſame God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.30, 38. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.32, 37. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.4, 5, 6. <hi>Deut:</hi> 6.4. <hi>Mar:</hi> 12.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>And from this Unitie of Eſſence neceſſarily followes the <hi>Cooperation</hi> of theſe three Perſons: as they have one and the ſame Eſſence; ſo they worke one and the ſame thing inſeparably. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1, 26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.17, 19, 21.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may this truth be confirmed, that theſe three Perſons have one and the ſame divine Eſſence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By theſe Arguments.</p>
               <p>Firſt becauſe the divine Eſſence being moſt ſimple, and infinite, is not ſubject to multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or diviſion; the divine Eſſence cannot be multiplied with the Perſons nor divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170467:54"/>
               <p> Secondly, becauſe the ſame divine Names are are given to each perſon. As the <hi>(a)</hi> Father is God, ſo the <hi>(b)</hi> Son is God, and the <hi>(c)</hi> Holy Ghoſt is God. As the <hi>(d)</hi> Father is Jehovah [or Lord] ſo the <hi>(e)</hi> Sonne is Jehova, and the <hi>(f)</hi> Holy Ghoſt is Jehova. <hi>(a) Joh:</hi> 17.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>(b) Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Act:</hi> 20.28. <hi>Rom:</hi> 9.5. <hi>(c) Act:</hi> 5.34. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>(d) Pſal. Pſal.</hi> 110.1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24. <hi>(e) Jer.</hi> 23.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Zech:</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>(f) Act.</hi> 28.25. compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.3, 5, 9.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe the ſame eſſentiall Attributes, and properties are given to each perſon. As the Father is eternall, So the <hi>(a)</hi> Sonne is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and the <hi>(b)</hi> Holy Ghoſt eternall. As the Father is omnipotent, ſo the <hi>(c)</hi> Sonne is om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, and the <hi>(d)</hi> Holy Ghoſt omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent &amp;c. <hi>(a) Joh.</hi> 1.1. and 17.5. <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.17. <hi>(b) Gen:</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>(c) Joh:</hi> 3.31. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. <hi>(d)</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the Diſtinction of theſe three Perſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although theſe three Perſons have one, and the ſame Eſſence, yet they differ really one from another; ſo that one is not, one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the other. The Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God: but the Father is not the Sonne; neither is the Holy Ghoſt, either Father or Sonne.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170467:55"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>Tell me more particularly wherein doe theſe three Perſons differ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They differ not in degree or dignitie: as they are coeſſentiall, ſo they are coequall. But theſe three perſons are diſtinct. <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.17, 18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Order and manner of ſubſiſting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In their Relative properties.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In manner of working.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seeing theſe three Perſons differ not in dignitie, why is one ſet before another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Although theſe three perſons be equall, yet one is in order before another, according to their manner of ſubſiſting: As the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sonne, and both of them before the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Math. chap.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>The Father is the Perſon without beginning, and therefore the firſt in order.</p>
               <p>The Sonne is of the Father alone, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſecond Perſon in order.</p>
               <p>The holy Ghoſt is of the Father and of the Sonne, and therefore the third Perſon in order.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seeing theſe three Perſons are distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their Relative Properties; tell me therefore, what kind of Properties are theſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are individuall, and incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may be obſerved from hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170467:55"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> That theſe three ſubſiſtencies, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne and Holy Ghoſt, are not improper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Perſons, becauſe they are diſtinguiſhed one from another by incommunicable indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall and perſonall properties?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Fathers relative, and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall propertie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be unbegotten, and to beget. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sonnes perſonall Propertie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To be begotten. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.18. and 3.16. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Holy Ghoſts Perſonall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To proceed. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seeing theſe three Perſons although they worke one and the ſame thing, yet not after the ſame manner, tell me therefore how are we to conceive of this third difference?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Each Perſon worketh according to the manner of his ſubſiſting. As Cooperation flowes from the Unitie of theſe three perſons in Eſſence; ſo this diſtinct manner of working flowes from the diſtinct manner of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Fathers manner of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As the Father is firſt in ſubſiſting, ſo he is firſt in working. The Father worketh of himſelf, by the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt: and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170467:56"/>therefore the Originall and beginning of all things is given to the Father.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Sonnes manner of working?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As the Sonne is from the Father, ſo he worketh from the Father, by the Holy Ghoſt: and therefore the diſpenſation of all things is given to the Sonne. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Spirits manner of working?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As the Spirit is both from the Father and the Sonne, ſo he worketh from them both. And becauſe he worketh from the Father and the Sonne therefore the Conſummation and finiſhing of all things is given to the Holy Ghoſt <hi>Joh:</hi> 16.13, 14, 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="doctrine">
               <head>DOCT. III. <hi>Of the Creation of the World.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat workes are attributed to God the Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Creation and Providence. We profeſſe to believe in <hi>God the Father, maker of Heaven and earth:</hi> a faithfull Creator, in which words we acknowledge God the Father to have crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the world once; and to preſerve and govern it alwaies. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Was Creation the firſt worke of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Creation was the firſt outward worke of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170467:56"/>God; but not ſimply the firſt Action of God. For Gods Decree is the Foundation of all his outward workes: God worketh according to his wiſe Counſell and eternall Decree. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God hath done in time, he purpoſed, and decreed to doe before all time. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods Purpoſe or decree?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an eternall action of Gods will, whereby he hath freely and immutably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of all things that ever have been or ſhall be. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.23. and 4.28. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.3.</p>
               <p>And this eternall decree God executeth in the Creation and Government of all things.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>What is Creation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A:</hi> Creation is the firſt part of the execution of Gods decree. whereby he made the world of nothing. <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.1. <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.3. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why is Creation eſpecially aſcribed to God the Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Fathers manner of working (to whom the Originall of all things is given) doth here principally appeare: for all things had their originall and beginning here, before God begunne this worke, there was not any thing but God the Creator.</p>
               <p>Now when creation is attributed to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded: for Creation, being an outward action,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170467:57"/>is common to the three perſons, the Father, the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt, did worke together in the Creation of the world. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1, 2, 26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Job.</hi> 33.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>By what meanes, with what Inſtruments, did God make the world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God uſed no other inſtrument but his powerfull word, God made all things by his word, that is, by his inward will, and effectuall command. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3, 6, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.5.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>What was the generall condition, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of all things, that were made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Every thing, that God made was good in his kind: and the whole worke was excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and beautifull, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>When did God begin this worke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Beginning of time. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How long did God continue working before the whole worke was finiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Six dayes: in the ſpace of ſix times 24. howres God finiſhed this great worke.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Could not God have perfected the whole worke in a moment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; but it ſeemed good to his wiſedome to take ſome dayes for the finiſhing of it, that we might more eaſily conceive, that the world was not made by chance, but by counſell: and might more diſtinctly conſider the parts of the world and every days worke.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170467:57"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>To what end did God make the world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For the communication of his goodneſſe, and the manifeſtation of his Glory. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Hitherto of the Creation of the World in generall: tell me now, what are the parts of the World?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are two
<list>
                     <item>The Habitations.</item>
                     <item>The Furniture, &amp; Inhabitants.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the Habitations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are either the higher habitations, the Heavens: or the lower, the earth and the Sea. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.6. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many Heavens are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are three Heavens: the third and higheſt Heaven; the upper Firmament where the Sunne, Moon, and Starres are ſet, and the lower Firmament, or Aire, wherein we breath and the birds fly. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.16, 17.17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What manner of Creature is the highest Heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The higheſt Heaven is a moſt glorious, immoveable, and unchangeable place, created in the firſt moment of time, where God is to be ſeen face to face, and therefore it is called <hi>the Habitation of his holineſſe.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.27. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.30.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170467:58"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>Whereof was the third Heaven made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Immediately of nothing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Creature is next unto the higheſt Heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The upper Firmament or Element of fire.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of this Element of fire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A,</hi> The fire is the higheſt of the Elements, moſt hot and lightſome. <hi>God ſaid let there be light. Gen:</hi> 1.3. Here by light (which is the moſt ſenſible qualitie of fire) we are to underſtand fire alſo which hath that qualitie.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the lower firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Element of Aire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God hath made the Aire equally capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of light and darkneſſe, and placed it next under the fire, as being neereſt of nature unto it: he hath ſtretched forth the Aire like a curtaine, to make a ſeparation between the waters above, (which are bound up in the Clouds) and the waters beneath. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.7. Hence this lower fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament or Element of Aire is divided into three parts, or Regions, the higheſt above the Clouds; the middle where the Clouds hang, and move; and the loweſt under the Clouds <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other elements are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Water and earth which are the lower Habitations. And becauſe theſe two lower Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments make but one globe, therefore in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170467:58"/>they are often comprehended, under this one terme Earth. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134.3. <hi>Act:</hi> 17.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the Element of water and of the creation of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The water is a cold and moiſt element, whoſe proper place is to ſucceed the Aire, and cover the Earth; but by Gods ſpeciall appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, part of it is raiſed and lifted up above his naturall place, into the middle Region of the Aire; and that part of it which is below, is ſo gathered together that it divides the Earth, and is called ſeas. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.6.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.7. and 148.4. <hi>Job.</hi> 26.8. and 38.37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.7. and 104.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How are we to conceive of the Element of Earth and of the Creation of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Earth is the dryeſt and heavieſt of all the Elements which he hath founded upon nothing: and although it hangeth upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet it ſtands firme, and immoveable. This Element the Lord made to appeare from under the waters, (which ſtood above the high mountaines, <hi>Pal.</hi> 14.6.) that it might be fit for habitation. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Job.</hi> 26.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.5. and 119.90.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whereof were theſe Elements of Fire, Aire, Water and Earth, made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Elements were made of that huge lump, or Maſſe, which is deſcribed, <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.2.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170467:59"/>
                  <hi>The Earth was without forme, and void, and darkneſſe was upon the face of the deep?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Seeing this Maſſe or Chaos was without forme and void, how was it ſuſtained?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It was ſuſtained preſerved and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed for a time by the comfortable and powerfull motion of the holy Ghoſt; for it is ſaid the ſpirit of God moved upon the face of the waters. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. Compare <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. with <hi>Deut:</hi> 32.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whereof was this huge Maſſe made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Immediately of nothing. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Having ſpoken of one part of the world, the Habitations, it followeth to ſpeake of the other part of the world, namely, the Furniture and Inhabitants: tell me therefore, what are the Inhabitants of the third and higheſt Heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The glorious Angels. <hi>Mat:</hi> 18.10. and 24.36. <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How are we to conceive of thoſe glorious Angels and of the Creation of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Angels are ſpirits created immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately of nothing, whoſe office is to miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to praiſe and celebrate his name, and to execute his commands: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are ſtiled <hi>Miniſtring ſpirits;</hi> and are ſaid to ſtand, before God as his immediate Miniſters, and Meſſengers alwaies readie to doe his pleaſure. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Pſ:</hi> 103.20. <hi>Iſ:</hi> 6.2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Lu:</hi> 1.19, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.21.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170467:59"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q. Seeing the Angels are miniſtring Spirits, how hath God fitted them for their Miniſtrie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God hath furniſhed them with excellent properties: as namely, with perſpicuitie of reaſon and libertie of will; with admirable ſtrength, and agilitie. 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 14.17. <hi>Mat:</hi> 24.36. 2 <hi>King:</hi> 10.35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.20. 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 1.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.2, 6. <hi>Dan:</hi> 9.21.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Furniture of the ſecond Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or upper Firmament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lights; the Sunne, the Moon and the Starrs, which are all Organs, and Receptacles of light and have power to caſt down their light upon the Earth. To theſe lightſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies God hath given a motive facultie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they move round about the Earth, that they might the better obtaine the ends for which they were created <hi>Job.</hi> 26. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the ends and uſes of thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt to give light and heate to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.15, 17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.6.</p>
               <p>Secondly to diſtinguiſh the night from the day: The Sunne was made to rule the day, the Moon and the Starres to rule the night: and to diſtinguiſh the day from the Month, and the Moneth from the yeare. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.8, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.19.</p>
               <p>Thirdly God made them for <hi>ſignes and for ſeaſons Gen.</hi> 1.14. to diſtinguiſh the ſet times
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170467:60"/>or Seaſons of the yeare as Spring, Summer, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne, and winter: and to be naturall ſignes and Inſtruments of thoſe naturall events, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in theſe Seaſons, as of ſtorms, tempeſts, faire weather, fruitfullneſſe, &amp;c. <hi>Gen:</hi> 8.22. <hi>Job.</hi> 9.9. <hi>Deut:</hi> 33.14. <hi>Job.</hi> 38.31, 32. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why are the Sunne and Moon called the greateſt lights?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are greateſt in their uſe: for they caſt down the greateſt portion of light, they give us more light then all the Starres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; they exerciſe moſt vertue upon theſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtiall bodies. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How hath God repleniſhed the lower Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, or Element of Aire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With Birds; with Clouds, Winds, and other Meteors. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.2, 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are the waters repleniſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With ſwimming Fiſhes, which God cauſed the waters to bring forth in abundance. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.20.21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How hath God adorned and repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the Earth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Earth is adorned within and without. The Creatures which adorn the bowels of the earth are the Mineralls, both Mettalls and Stones. The Creatures which adorne the face of the earth are the plants, both the leſſer, and the greater, the leſſer as graſſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170467:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>herbes, flowers, Corne; and the greater Trees. The Earth, being thus adorned, was repleniſhed with inhabitants. The Inhabitants of the Earth, are theſe: Birds, which God made to fly in the Aire; and commanded to multiply upon the Earth; and therefore they have a double place they move in the Aire, and reſt on the Earth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.20, 22.</p>
               <p>Beaſts, both tame, and wild, going, and creeping. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.24, 25.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt Inhabitant is Man.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may be obſerved generally concerning theſe Creatures which fill Heaven and Earth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All theſe Creatures are called Gods Hoſts, and Servants they ſtand all in order like an Armie ſet in Battell aray, and are alwaies readie to obey the command of God their Creator; who is therefore ſtiled <hi>the Lord of hoſts. Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 119.91. <hi>Deu.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Jud.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.12. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.19. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2 <hi>v.</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seeing Creation was a worke of ſix dayes, tell me therefore, what was created the firſt day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The third Heaven; the glorious Angels; that huge Maſſe which was the firſt Matter of all inconſtant, and corruptible things; and the Element of Fire. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>Although the Angels be not expreſly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by Moſes in the hiſtorie of the Creation, yet it may be gathered out of Scripture, that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170467:61"/>they were created before the third day. Theſe Sonnes of God did ſing and ſhoot when God layd the foundations of the earth, <hi>Job.</hi> 38.4, 6, 7. and therefore it is moſt probable they were created the firſt day together with the higheſt Heaven which is their proper habitation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.2.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was made the ſecond day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Element of Aire. <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was made the third day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The water and the Earth which make but one globe: The plants and the Mineralls. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.9, 10, 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was made the fourth day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Thoſe Heavenly bodies, the Sunne, the Moone and the Starres which garniſh the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per firmament, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was made the fifth day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The fiſhes of the Sea, and the Foules of the Aire <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.20.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q: What was the worke of the ſixth night and day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. In the night thereof (as is probable) God made the Beaſts of the Earth, and in the day thereof God made man in both ſexes, that is both man and woman. <hi>Pſal</hi> 104.20, 22, 23. <hi>Gen:</hi> 1.24, 25, 26, 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What divine Attributes hath God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the Creation of the world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Chiefly theſe three; his Power, Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Goodneſſe. In this great worke of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170467:61"/>Creation, we may plainly ſee the footſteps of Gods infinite and eternall power; of his admirable wiſedome; and his incomparable Goodneſſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 104.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What argument of Gods Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie may be obſerved from his worke of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe that follow:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all things were made of nothing. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That God made the World, and all things therein, by his word, that is, by his inward will, and powerfull Commands. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 33.6, 9. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 148.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That God made the huge earth, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt of all the Elements, to hang immoveable in the midſt of the Aire without any pillar to ſupport it. <hi>Job.</hi> 26.7. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10.12. and <hi>chap.</hi> 51.15.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The multitude of the Creatures which fill Heaven and earth; theſe Hoſts, and Armies of God are innumerable. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 33.22. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 104.24, 25.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The ſtrength God hath given to many Creatures: as to Angels, to the Sunne; to the Winds; to the Leviathan: and to divers Beaſts. See <hi>Job.</hi> 39, <hi>verſ.</hi> 40.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170467:62"/>and <hi>chap.</hi> 41. <hi>v.</hi> 2. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>Job.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.21.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That God made the earth fruitfull, before he made the ſecond, and ordinarie cauſes, which doe naturally produce this Effect. God made the earth to bring forth graſſe and corne, and trees, before the raine deſcended upon it, and before there was a man to till the ground; yea before thoſe Heavenly bodies the Sunne, the Moon and the Starres were created to ſend downe their influences upon the earth. <hi>Geneſ. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That God hath given power, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to living Creatures to bring forth the like unto themſelves, for the continuance of their ſeverall kinds: Herein appeareth as the Wiſedome, ſo the Power of God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Argument of Gods Wiſedome may be obſerved from this worke of Creation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The beautie of the Heavens with their ornaments. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.5. <hi>Job.</hi> 26.13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.12. and 51.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Infinite varietie of viſible Creatures: the manifold wiſedome of God appeareth, in creating ſo may diverſe kinds of birds, of beaſts, of fiſhes, of trees, of herbs, of Metalls of ſtones &amp;c. yea the wiſedome of God appeareth in the exquiſite frame of the ſmalleſt living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:170467:62"/> 3. The fitneſſe of every Creature for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end: the fitneſſe of the Habitations for their ſeverall Inhabitants.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſubordination of the Creatures: God hath ſet the Creatures in ſuch excellent order that they keep their ſeverall ſtations, and are ſerviceable, and uſefull one to another. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.91.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The naturall prudence, and providence which God hath given to many unreaſonable Creatures. <hi>Jer:</hi> 8.7. <hi>Job.</hi> 39.17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.6, 7, 8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.24, 28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other Argument of Gods Wiſedome may be obſerved from this worke of Creation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Order, which God obſerved in this worke of creation is another Argument of his wiſedome. For the Elements which are ſimple bodies, were firſt created, and then mixt bodies which are compounded of theſe Elements: And here God proceeded from the things that are leſſe perfect to thoſe that are more perfect, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he came to the perfecteſt: as from plants which have a ſingle life, namely, a growing life to fiſh, and foules, and beaſts, which have a compound life, and from them to Man, which hath (beſides vegetation, and ſence) a Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule, whereby he liveth a reaſonable life.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Argument of Gods perfection, and Goodneſs may be obſerved from this worke of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170467:63"/> 1. The goodneſſe, and Perfection of every Creature in his kind. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Excellencie; and perfection of the whole worke; for the world was created ſo good and perfect that it could not be better: Not that Gods power is limited but the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is limited. the creature was not capable of more perfection.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Although God hath made the world ſo good, and perfect yet there is an infinite diſtance between that perfection, of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Perfection of the Creator; for the perfection of the Creature; (even of the whole world) is finite, but the perfection of God is infinite.</p>
               <p>Finally, the Goodneſſe and bountifullneſſe of God appeareth in the large proviſion he hath made for the neceſſities of every one of his Creatures <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why was man made laſt of all the Creatures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt becauſe man was the Nobleſt of all viſible Creatures.</p>
               <p>Secondly becauſe he would have man boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully provided for, before he brought him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, to the end he might be ſtirred up to glorifie God for all thoſe creatures which are made for his uſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly becauſe man was an Epitome of the whole worke: and is therefore not unfitly ſtiled, <hi>A little world</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What things are moſt remarkable in the Creation of Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170467:63"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the Hiſtorie of Mans Creation, theſe things are remarkable:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the holy Trinitie is brought in as it were deliberating, and conſulting about the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this excellent Creature, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Let us make man.</hi> Where as other Creatures were were made by a ſimple Command; Man was not made without a divine Conſultation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That man was made in the Image and likneſſe of God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That man was made part after part; firſt his bodie then his Soule. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas in the Creation of other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, male and Female were made together, it was not ſo here but firſt the Man was created, and then the Woman. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seeing man was created in the Image of God, tell me wherein did this Image conſist?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the puritie and perfection of Mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the excellencie of thoſe endowments, which God beſtowed upon him, whereby man was able in a ſpeciall manner to reſemble God his Creator. <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was the ſubject of the Image?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The whole Perſon conſiſting of bodie and Soule. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Tell me more particularly, how or wherein did Man reſemble God his Creator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. In thoſe noble Faculties of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and will, wherewith the Soule of man was endowed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170467:64"/> 2. In Knowledge, and wiſedome; in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Righteouſneſſe which did perfect theſe faculties. Man was endued with admirable Wiſedome and Knowledge; as appeareth by his naming of the Creatures, when they came before him, according to their ſeverall natures and diſpoſitions. Man was endowed with ſuch holineſſe, and Righteouſneſſe that he was able in all his actions to reſemble the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and righteouſneſſe of God his Creator. Now in theſe excellent gifts, and habits of Wiſedome, Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe, did the Image of God principally conſiſt. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.19, 20. and 22, 23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Was the Image of God stamped upon mans body alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, ſome ſparkes of Gods image were to be ſeen even in mans bodie, conſidered as united to the ſoule, and making one perſon with it: for the body was made a moſt fit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument for the ſoule, being ſo compoſed that the ſoule might conveniently uſe it for all workes of holineſſe, and righteouſneſſe. As a bright candle ſhines through a cleare Lanterne; ſo thoſe excellent qualities which were in the Soule of Man did ſhine through his bodie. And Mans body ſhould have been immortall (if he had continued in his integritie) together with his ſoule. Moreover there was ſuch a grace and majeſtie in the perſon, eſpecially in the face of man; that the other creatures could not look
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170467:64"/>upon him without feare &amp; reverence. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5:12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there any thing alſo wherein man did reſemble God his Creator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, in his dominion, and rule over the Creatures. As God is abſolute Lord over all Creatures, ſo he made man his Lord deputie under him: and therefore the Creatures were brought unto him as to their Lord, to ſee how he would name them. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein did that dominion which God gave man over the creatures conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In a moſt free uſe of the Creature for Gods glory for his own neceſſity and lawfull delight. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28, 29.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seeing man conſiſteth of a body and of a ſoule, tell me therefore, whereof was mans body made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Of the duſt of the Earth, with the reſt of the Elements. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. and 3.19. <hi>Job.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What manner of Body was it made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God formed and faſhioned the Body of Man after a fingular manner, above the bodies of other Creatures, that it might be a fit habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his reaſonable ſoule. It was made of an exquiſite temper; of an erect and ſtraight figure; and furniſhed with all ſuch Organs, as were neceſſarie for comelineſs or uſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How was the ſoule of man made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It was made of nothing by the inſufflati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or inſpiration of God: God immediately
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170467:65"/>breathed it into the bodie. It was not firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and then inſpired; but created, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired together. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What manner of ſoule was it made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Reaſonable ſoule, endowed with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers excellent faculties, and of that nature that it is able to ſubſiſt, and live of it ſelfe, and to give life unto the Bodie; and therefore being joyned to the bodie, which God had formed. man became a living and Reaſonable Creature <hi>Gen:</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the creation of the woman?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Womans body was not made imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately of the foure Elements but of one of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> ribs, man being caſt into a deep ſleep. The Soule of the Woman was not produced from <hi>Adams</hi> ſoule, as her bodie from his bodie, but created of God and inſpired into the bodie which God had builded. As the ſoule of the man was created immediately of nothing; in like manner was the ſoule of the Woman. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.21, 2. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.23.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why did God make the Woman?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God ſaw it was not convenient and comfortable for man to live alone, and amongſt the reſt of the Creatures there was not one fit to be his Companion. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18, 20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How was the woman fitted for the Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:170467:65"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Woman was made an help meet for man, in regard ſhe was made every way like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him namely,</p>
               <p>Firſt, in kind, and nature; ſuch as were the Body, and ſoule of the Man, ſuch alſo were the body and ſoule of the Woman.</p>
               <p>Secondly, faculties gifts &amp; endowment, even the whole image of God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29.</p>
               <p>Thirdly in ſtate and condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="doctrine">
               <head>DOCT. IIII. A larger Expoſition of <hi>Divine Providence?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. <hi>HItherto of the worke of Creation: tell me now, What is Divine Providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Providence is the ſecond part of the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Gods Decree, whereby he preſerveth, and governeth all the Creatures which he hath made, and provideth for every one of them. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Pfal.</hi> 136.25. &amp; 145.15, 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. and 5.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. What are the ſeverall Acts and operations of Gods generall Providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are chiefly five.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God foreſeeth the wants and neceſſities of his creatures; whatſoever is needfull for the preſervation of any creature. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.32. <hi>Act:</hi> 15.18.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170467:66"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God prepareth for his Creatures, and beſtoweth upon them whatſoever he knoweth to be needfull for their preſervation. For the preſerving of their ſeverall kinds he hath given unto plants the power of propagation: and to ſenſitive Creatures the power of Generation, with a ſtrong deſire of poſteritie. And for the preſerving of Singulars he giveth them food and nouriſhment and ſhelter alſo, to keep them from outward violence. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.25. <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145, 15, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.10, 11, 12, 14, 16, 17, 18, 21, 27, 28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God ſuſtaineth all his creatures; as their eſſence and being: ſo thoſe powers faculties and qualities which he hath beſtowed upon them. <hi>Act:</hi> 17.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God moveth and worketh in, and with the Creature: God is an univerſall, and effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of all motions in the creature. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the fifth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God doth order the Creature to an End; and diverts every Creature to his proper end. As God hath made every Creature for an end, ſo he preſerves the Creature for it &amp; guids the Creature to it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30 25.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the generall ends of divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:170467:66"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> The good of the Creature: and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Creator and Governour. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the divine providence diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is either ordinarie or extraordinarie</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods ordinarie Providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods ordinarie providence is that whereby he provideth for his Creatures, by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie meanes. Now ſeeing this is Gods uſuall, and ordinarie manner of working, both in workes of Nature, and in workes of Grace; therefore to depend upon Gods Extraordinarie Providence without uſing the ordinarie meanes when the Lord doth afford them, is <hi>to tempt God. Pſal.</hi> 147.8, 9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.21, 22. <hi>Act:</hi> 14.17. <hi>Rom:</hi> 10.13, 14, 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods extraordinarie providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods extraordinarie Providence is that whereby he provideth for his Creatures extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily, and by miracle. Sometimes God leaps over the ſecond cauſes and workes the end without the Meanes: and this is called Gods <hi>immediate Providence.</hi> Thus God ſuſtained <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> 40. dayes together without meat or drink. Sometimes God worketh above natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall meanes, and by miracle. Thus the Iſraelites were ſuſtained fortie yeares together in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, by Gods extraordinarie providence. Thus God preſerved <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> in the midſt of the burning fierie fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace miraculouſly. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.21, 22. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170467:67"/>
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 15.16. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.4, 6. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.28. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3, 4. &amp; 29.5. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.20, 21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Miracle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Miracle is an extraordinarie worke, exceeding the abilitie of all ſecond cauſes, as to make the Sunne ſtand ſtill, to make the Sunne goe back to raiſe the dead, and the like. Now this is proper to God to worke true miracles See <hi>Pſal:</hi> 72.18. and 86.10. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.12, 13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.8., <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.43, 44. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Object of divine providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The providence of God extendeth to all things whatſoever <hi>not one ſparrow is forgotten of God, the very haires of our heads are all numbred.</hi> There is not any Creature either in Heaven or in Earth, there is not any thing belonging to any Creature but the Providence of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth unto it. As the glorious Angels, the proper inhabitants of the higheſt heaven, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of Gods Government; ſo the baſeſt wormes that creep upon the earth, are under the eye of God providence. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29, 30. <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doth the providence, of God extend to thoſe things which come to paſſe by caſualtie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; as the providence of God extendeth to all things great and ſmall; ſo to all events neceſſarie and contingent, or caſuall. <hi>The lot is caſt into the lap; but the whole diſpoſing
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170467:67"/>thereof is of the Lord. Prov.</hi> 16.33 <hi>Deuteron.</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. compared with <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.13. <hi>Jon.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But doth any thing come to paſſe by chance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nothing cometh to paſſe by meer chance. Indeed thoſe Events which were not foreſeen, or intended by us, the ſecond cauſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are ignorant of, are called <hi>caſuall</hi> and ſuch things are ſaid to fall out caſually, or by chance. But no event is ſimply caſuall, that is ſo caſuall as that the providence of God ſhould not extend to it. For divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath an hand in governing thoſe events, which ſeem caſuall to us, that are ignorant of the ſecond cauſes of them. We muſt not therefore aſcribe that to Fortune which is to be attributed to divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, What cometh to us by chance, we muſt make account, it is of Gods ſending. See <hi>Mark. chap.</hi> 14.13, 16. 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May Chriſtians uſe theſe termes of chance, and Fortune?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Religion doth not abſolutely forbid us to uſe the terme <hi>chance or fortune;</hi> but theſe are Heatheniſh words and therefore Chriſtians muſt uſe them warily and ſparingly. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Deu.</hi> 22.6.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170467:68"/>
               <p> Q. <hi>What other particulars are comprehended under the generall object of divine Providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As the providence of God extendeth to all things great and ſmall; neceſſarie and caſuall; ſo it extendeth to all Actions, and to all Events, good and evill, <hi>Proverb.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth the Providence of God extend to evill and ſinfull actions? Is God the Author of any ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Farre be it from us to think that God is the Author of that ſinne, whereof he is the Avenger, the Lord hateth, forbiddeth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, and puniſheth all ſinne, and therefore he is not the Author of any ſinne. We may rather accuſe the Sunne which is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of light, to be the cauſe of darkneſſe then accuſe God who is goodneſſe it ſelfe to be the cauſe and Author of ſinne. Yea God is ſo farre from being the Author of ſinne, that he would never ſuffer it, were it not for the good that he can draw out of it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 5.5. and 92.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How then doth the Providence of God extend to evill and ſinfull actions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is neither the Author nor Actor of any Sin; nor yet an idle ſpectator of ſinners; but he acteth the part of a Judge, and of a Governour. The Lord hath a powerfull hand in governing the tranſgreſſions of all ſinners;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170467:68"/>yet ſo as he is moſt free from all ſtaine of ſinne and unrighteouſneſſe. Read and conſider theſe teſtimonies of Scripture. <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.5, 7, 8. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.25. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.21. and 5.1, 2. and 9.34. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11, 12. and 16.10, 11. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 10.15. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.19, 20, 23. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.23. and 4.27, 28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24, 25, 26, 28. and 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how can the Lord ſo powerfully, and effectually governe ſinners, and yet be free from all ſtaine of ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As a man that ringeth a crackt bell is the cauſe of the motion of the Bell but not of the jarring of it: and as a man that rides upon a lame horſe, when he puts him forward is the cauſe of the horſe his going but not of his haulting: ſo here God is the univerſall cauſe and Author of every action, and motion of the Sinner, (for all Actions naturally, and ſimply conſidered, are good) but the Divell, and Mans Concupiſcence, and corrupt will are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Authors of that evill, or faultineſſe, which cleaveth to the action. <hi>Act:</hi> 17.28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may this be further cleared?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As a skilfull workman can uſe an ill tool well, and worke artificially with it: in like manner, the Lord can uſe thoſe wicked, and fooliſh men, which are the Inſtruments of his providence, well and wiſely. The Inſtrument we know is wholly ſubject to the principall Agent, without infuſing any qualitie into it. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170467:69"/>which wicked men being the inſtruments of Gods providence, doe wickedly and ſinfully; the Lord doth juſtly and righteouſly. For the will and purpoſe of Sinners which are Gods Inſtruments, differ from the will and purpoſe of that righteous God, which over-ruleth and governeth theſe inſtruments.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Can you make this more plaine by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This may plainly be ſeen in the crucifying of Chriſt. As <hi>Judas,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up Chriſt to death; ſo God the Father alſo is ſaid to have done the ſame: but <hi>Judas</hi> did it out of diſcontentment, and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the end he might obtain the mony he deſired. The <hi>Jewes</hi> of malice and ignorance, to the end that Chriſt ſhould not raigne over them; <hi>Pilate</hi> out of ambition and feare, to the end he might pleaſe the people, and keep his place, whereas God delivered up Chriſt to death out of love to his Church, and for the ſalvation of his people. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.16. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.23. and 4.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.18, 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Joh:</hi> 11.48. <hi>John</hi> 19.12, 13, 15, 16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What followeth from hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Seing that wicked men are the proper Actors of their own ſinnes; though they be as Inſtruments in Gods hand, yet they are active Inſtruments which underſtand and will what they doe; &amp; ſeeing that which ſinners doe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170467:69"/>the Lord who governeth all ſinners doth righteouſly: therefore God may juſtly puniſh ſinners for doing that, wherein they have been the Inſtruments of his Providence. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.5, 6, 12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth the providence of God extend to good and evill events?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God is the Author of all Events, good and evill. As all bleſſings, ſo all Afflictions, and Judgements come from the Lords hand, and by his ſpeciall appointment: Whoſoever be the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, or Meſſenger to convey any bleſſing unto us, God is the Giver of it. Whoſoever be the bringer of any Afliction, God is the ſender of it. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.7. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.38. <hi>Jer:</hi> 25.15.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When the wicked proſper and flouriſh in the world, when the Godly groane under many preſſures, afflictions, and croſſes, is God the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſer both of the proſperitie of the one, and of the adverſitie of the other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, all Calamities and Judgements, as warre, ſickneſſe, famine, &amp;c. are the Arrowes of the almighty, whereſoever they light, and all outward Bleſſings, as peace, health, plentie, all come from Gods bountifull hand, even when they are beſtowed upon wicked men. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.2. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 91.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.17, 19. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.45. <hi>Act:</hi> 14.17.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:170467:70"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Q. How can the afflicted eſtate of the Godly, and the proſperitie of the wicked, ſtand with the juſt and wiſe providence of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we deſire to ſee and diſcerne the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Juſtice of divine providence, we muſt look upon theſe works of God, not by the light of our naturall Reaſon, but by the light of Gods Word. We cannot judge aright of the whole providence of God by a little part of it. We ſee but a little part of divine providence here in this world; an other part of it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth immediately after death; and the laſt (which is the greateſt) part of it at the laſt Judgement. Now if we lay all the parts of Gods providence together, if we goe into the Sanctuarie of God, and weigh all things in the Ballance of the Sanctuarie, then we ſhall ſee the Wiſedome and Juſtice of divine Providence. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.16. &amp; 73.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.1.</p>
               <p>Q: <hi>But doth not God oftentimes deale better with the wicked, then with the righteous in this world? is not the proſperitie of the wicked, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be deſired then the afflicted eſtate of the righteous?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: although the Lord be kind and bountifull to the wicked here, yet he doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his grace and mercie, and goodneſſe much more to the godly, then to the wicked. For the godly, notwithſtanding the many Afflictions
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170467:70"/>that befall them here, are in a bleſſed condition: whereas the wicked notwithſtanding their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperitie (which is glorious in the eye of the World) are miſerable and curſed. <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.12. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10, 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may it appeare that the godly, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the many afflictions that befall them here are in a bleſſed condition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By theſe Conſiderations following <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Godly though they live under the croſſe yet are adorned with heavenly vertues and <hi>bleſſed with all ſpirituall bleſſings in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> All their ſinnes are remitted, and all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neceſſarie to ſalvation, are beſtowed upon them. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Joh:</hi> 16.33. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The bitter Cup of Affliction is ſweetned unto them. As their afflictions abound, ſo their Conſolations abound alſo: the Lord gives them ſtrength, and comfort proportionable to that Burthen of Affliction which he layes upon them. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their Afflictions being ſanctifyed bring forth excellent fruits and ſo become matter of rejoycing unto them. The Lord by afflictions repaireth his glorious image in the Soules of his Children, and ſo fits them for his Kingdome. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10 11.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170467:71"/> 4. The Lord upholds them in their greateſt preſſures with the certaine hope of future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; and gives them a Joyfull deliverance in his good time. <hi>Job.</hi> 19.25. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35.37. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19. and 37.37. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Job.</hi> 42.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may it appeare, that the wicked notwithſtandeng their outward proſperitie, which is glorious in the eye of the world, are miſerable, and curſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By theſe conſiderations following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The wicked though they flouriſh in the world yet in Gods ſight are condemned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and abominable. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When the wicked man holds a full cup of pleaſure in one hand, he holds a cup of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Judgement in the other hand and drinks deep of it: for God gives him over to blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind, to hardneſſe of heart, &amp;c. Now of all plagues, and Judgements, which are inflicted upon ſinners, theſe ſpirituall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments though they be ſecret and inſenſible, yet are moſt fearfull. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The wicked have many ſtinges and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Conſcience that the world takes noe notice of, which makes their earthly delights, and pleaſures bitter unto them <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas the goodneſſe of God ſhould leade and allure ungodly men to repentance, becauſe it hath not this effect in them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170467:71"/>it deprives them of excuſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The proſperitie of the wicked is ſhort and uncertaine: but their ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is certaine and inevitable: <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.5, 8. and 21.17. <hi>Pfal.</hi> 73.18, 19, 20. and 129.6. <hi>Pov.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12, 13. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The preſent proſperitie of ungodly men makes way to their heavier Judgement; and damnation: the longer they are ſpared the neerer is the cup both of temporall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Judgement unto them, and the deeper ſhall they drink of it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.35. and <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7.11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of that part of divine providence which beginneth when this life is ended? how will God deale with the Godly and with the wicked in the world to come?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the world to come God will manifeſt his exact Juſtice in puniſhing the wicked, and his mercie and fidelitie in rewarding the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: partly at death; and partly at the laſt Judgement. The Scripture teacheth, that the Lord <hi>hath made the wicked for the day of evill.</hi> Now both the day of death and the day of Judgement, are evill dayes to the wicked, but good and joyfull dayes to the godly. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 62.12. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 58.11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Tell me more particularly how doth God deale with the godly at death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The godly when they goe out of this world ſhall carrie none of their Calamities, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170467:72"/>Miſeries with them, but they ſhall reſt from all their afflictions ſorrowes and labours: and their <hi>good workes ſhall follow them.</hi> When the righteous die, their Soules are carryed imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the <hi>Angels into Abrams boſome;</hi> and their bodyes ſhall reſt in their Graves as in perfumed Beds till the laſt day; <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. and 23.43. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What ſhall be the eſtate of the wicked (which proſper here) at Death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The wicked, when they goe out of this world, ſhall carry none of their Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and pleaſures with them; but inſtead of theſe, they ſhall carry a Bundle of their Sins; their Tranſgreſſions ſhall follow them. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that proſper &amp; flouriſh here, are like unto Sheep or Kine, that are put into fat paſtures to be prepared for the ſhambles: for when they die their Soules are ſent immediately to Hell; and their bodies are carryed to the darke dungeon of the Grave: and their Soules, and bodies being thus ſeparated, Death ſhall feed upon their Bodies, and the Worme that never dyeth ſhall feed upon their Soules. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Luk:</hi> 16.22, 23. <hi>P.</hi> 49.14. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.44.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are we to conceive of the third, and laſt (which is not the leaſt) part of divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? how will God deale with the Godly and with the wicked at the great day of Judgement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The great day of Judgement, will be a day of triumph, and of perfect redemption to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170467:72"/>the godly; but a day of wrath, and of eternall perdition to the wicked. Now the Juſtice of God ſeemes to be obſerved in the preſent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of the wicked, and the many preſſures of the righteous: but then the exact Juſtice of God ſhall be declared, and manifeſted to all the world. Now many particular Judgements of God are ſo ſecret and hidden, that we are not able to give a ſufficient reaſon of them: but then the wiſedome and Juſtice of ſecreteſt diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall appeare to men and Angels. Now the godly are counted <hi>miſerable,</hi> but then their happineſſe will appeare to all the world, when they ſhall heare that ſweet Sentence <hi>Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father inherit the Kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi> Now the wicked are counted and called happy; but then the miſerable curſed condition of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall appeare to all the world, when they ſhall heare that dreadfull Sentence, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire prepared for the Divell and his Angels, Luk.</hi> 21.28. <hi>Job.</hi> 21.30. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Rom:</hi> 11.33. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.15.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
